<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<publications>

  <title>DBIS: Publication</title>

  <publication type="techreport" bib-id="may-lausen-tr136-infoextr" local-id="TR136-InfoExtr">

    <!-- Details of publication 1 -->

    <shorttitle> TR 136: Information Extraction from the Web with Florid</shorttitle>

    <techreport>Technical Report 136</techreport>

    <institute> Institute for Information</institute>

    <university>University of Freiburg </university>

    <date>March</date>

    <year>2000</year>

    <title>Information Extraction from the Web</title>

    <authors>

      <author>Wolfgang May</author>

      <author>Georg Lausen</author>

    </authors>

    <!-- Abstract of Publication 1 -->

    <abstract>

      <htmlfrag xmlns:ht="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">

        <p>

          The goal of information extraction from the Web is to provide an integrated
          view on data from autonomous, heterogeneous information sources. The main
          problem with current wrapper/mediator approaches is that they rely on very
          different formalisms and tools for wrappers and mediators, thus leading to an
          "impedance mismatch" between the wrapper and mediator level. Additionally,
          most approaches nowadays are restricted to access information only from a
          fixed set of sources. On the other hand,
          <i>generic</i>
           Web
          <i>querying</i>

          approaches are restricted to pure syntactical and structural queries and do
          not deal with semantical issues.

        </p>

        <p> In this paper, we discuss an integrated architecture for Web exploration,
          wrapping, mediation, and querying. Our system is based on a unified framework
          - i.e., data model and language - in which all tasks are performed. We regard
          the Web and its contents as a unit, represented in an object-oriented data
          model: the Web structure, given by its hyperlinks, the parse-trees of Web
          pages, and its contents are all included in the internal world model of the
          system. The advantage of this unified view is that the same data manipulation
          and querying language can be used for the Web structure and the application-
          level model: The model is complemented by a rule-based object-oriented
          language which is extended by Web access capabilities and structured document
          analysis. Thus, accessing Web pages, wrapping, mediating, and querying
          information can be done using the same language. </p>

        <p>
          This integration also allows for data-driven Web exploration which is
          independent from a given network of individual predefined wrappers and
          mediators. Thus, in addition to the classical wrapper and mediator
          functionality, a system with this architecture can be equipped with

          <i>Web navigation</i>

          and

          <i>exploration</i>

          functionality. Queries to existing Web indexing and searching engines can
          also be integrated.

        </p>

        <p> In particular, we present a methodology for reusing generic rule patterns
          for typical extraction, integration, and restructuring tasks using this
          framework. In an abstract sense, the system contains a universal wrapper,
          which can be applied to arbitrary Web pages that the system learns about
          during information processing. Equipped with suitably intelligent rules, the
          system can potentially explore initially unknown parts of the Web, thus
          coping with the steady growth of the Web. </p>

        <p>
          We show the practicability of our approach by using the

          <a shape="rect" href="http://www.informatik.uni-freiburg.de/~dbis/florid/"> FLORID</a>

            system. The approach is illustrated by two case-studies.

        </p>

      </htmlfrag>

    </abstract>

    <!-- Comment of Publication 1 -->

    <comment>

      <htmlfrag xmlns:ht="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">

        <p>

          <a shape="rect" href="TR136-InfoExtr.ps">[ps-File]</a>

        </p>

        <p> Excerpts of this work have been published in </p>

        <ul>

          <li>

            <reference target="may-idm-99">Modeling and Querying Structure and Contents
              of the Web</reference>
             ,
            <i>International Workshop on Internet Data Management (IDM'99)</i>

              , Florence, Sept. 2, 1999,

          </li>

          <li>

            <reference target="may-ludaescher-lausen-himmeroeder-wwwcm-99">A Unified
              Framework for Wrapping, Mediating and Restructuring Information from the
              Web</reference>
             ,
            <i>International Workshop on the World-Wide Web and Conceptual Modeling
              (WWWCM'99)</i>
            , Paris, Nov. 15-18, 1999,

          </li>

          <li>

            <reference target="may-adc2k-00">
                An Integrated Architecture for Exploring, Wrapping, Mediating
                and Restructuring Information from the Web
              </reference>
             ,

            <i>
                Australasian Database Conference
                (ADC 2000)
              </i>

              , Canberra, Jan. 31 -Feb. 3, 2000,

          </li>

          <li>

            <reference target="may-dagstuhl-99">Slides</reference>

              have been presented at

            <i>Dagstuhl-Seminar "Declarative Data Access on the Web"</i>

              , Sept. 12-17, 1999, Schloss Dagstuhl, Germany.

          </li>

          <li>

              The
            <reference target="may-TR-Mondial-99">MONDIAL</reference>

              Case Study describes a practical application.

          </li>

        </ul>

        <p>

            A
          <reference target="lausen-may-IS-04">journal version</reference>

            appeared with
          <em>Informations Systems</em>
          , 2004.

        </p>

      </htmlfrag>

    </comment>

  </publication>

  <!-- Publication 2  -->

  <publication type="conference" bib-id="may-adc2k-00" local-id="adc2k">

    <!-- Details -->

    <shorttitle> Abstract ADC2000</shorttitle>

    <conference short="ADC 2000"> Australasian Database Conference (ADC 2000)</conference>

    <place>Canberra, Australia</place>

    <date>Jan. 31 - Feb. 3</date>

    <year>2000</year>

    <month>1</month>

    <day>31</day>

    <proceedings>Australian Computer Science Communications, Vol. 2, No. 2, IEEE CS Press</proceedings>

    <page>82-89</page>

    <title>An Integrated Architecture for Exploring, Wrapping, Mediating and
    Restructuring Information from the Web </title>

    <authors>

      <author>Wolfgang May</author>

    </authors>

    <!-- Abstract Pub 2 -->

    <abstract>

      <htmlfrag xmlns:ht="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">

        <p> The goal of information extraction from the Web is to provide an
        integrated view on heterogeneous information sources. A main problem with
        current wrapper/mediator approaches is that they rely on very different
        formalisms and tools for wrappers and mediators, thus leading to an
        "impedance mismatch" between the wrapper and mediator level. Additionally,
        most approaches currently are tailored to access information from a fixed set
        of sources. In this paper, we discuss an architecture where Web exploration,
        wrapping, mediation, and querying is done in an integrated system. Such an
        architecture reveals significant advantages in combination with a unified
        framework - i.e., data model and language - in which all tasks are done. Our
        approach is based on a unified model of the application-level information and
        the relevant fragment of the Web, and on an integrated language for accessing
        the Web, wrapping, mediating, and querying information. In this world model,
        in contrast to other approaches, the relevant part of the Web becomes a part
        of the internal world model of the system. This allows for a data-driven Web
        exploration which is independent from a given network of individual
        predefined wrappers and mediators. Thus, in addition to the classical
        wrapping and mediating functionality, a system in this architecture can be
        equipped with Web navigation and exploration functionality. In an abstract
        sense, the system comprises a universal wrapper which can be applied to
        arbitrary Web data sources which become known to the system during
        information processing. Equipped with suitably intelligent rules, the system
        can potentially explore before unknown parts of the Web, thus coping with the
        steady growth of the Web. The architecture is implemented in the FLORID
        system. </p>

      </htmlfrag>

    </abstract>

    <!-- Comment Pub 2 -->

    <comment>

      <htmlfrag xmlns:ht="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">

        <p>

          <a shape="rect" href="adc2000sl.ps"> [Slides]</a>

        </p>

      </htmlfrag>

    </comment>

  </publication>

  <!-- Publication 3 -->

  <publication type="conference" bib-id="may-gi-idb2000-00" local-id="gi-idb2000">

    <!-- Details Pub 3 -->

    <shorttitle>Abstract IDB2000</shorttitle>

    <conference short="IDB2000">

      <a shape="rect" href="http://wwwiti.cs.uni-       magdeburg.de/iti_db/workshops/IDB2000/">Workshop Internet-Datenbanken</a>

      , GI-Jahrestagung 2000

    </conference>

    <place>Berlin, Germany</place>

    <date>Sept. 19</date>

    <year>2000</year>

    <month>9</month>

    <day>19</day>

    <proceedings>Published in Technical Report No. 12, Fak. f. Informatik, Univ.
    Magdeburg, 2000</proceedings>

    <page>31-45</page>

    <title>Handling XML with a Deductive Database System</title>

    <authors>

      <author>Wolfgang May</author>

    </authors>

    <!-- Abstract Pub 3 -->

    <abstract>

      <htmlfrag xmlns:ht="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">

        <p> We propose an integration of XML with F-Logic, a deductive object-
        oriented database framework. The F-Logic data model is in fact a
        semistructured data model, exhibiting many similarities with the XML/DOM data
        model: there is a canonical mapping from XML to a fragment of F-Logic. The
        advantages of the integration are that the full expressiveness of F-Logic
        (and the functionality of the Florid system) can be applied to the data,
        providing an intuitive language for view definitions, updates, schema
        reasoning, Web exploration, integration (also with non-XML sources) etc.
        Especially, extended XML features, such as XML Schema or XLink can easily be
        prototypically implemented and evaluated. </p>

      </htmlfrag>

    </abstract>

    <!-- Comment Pub 3 -->

    <comment>

      <htmlfrag xmlns:ht="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">

        <p>

          <a shape="rect" href="idb2000.ps"> [Postscript]</a>

        </p>

        <p>

          <a shape="rect" href="idb2000sl.ps"> [Slides]</a>

        </p>

      </htmlfrag>

    </comment>

  </publication>

  <!-- Publication 4 -->

  <publication type="techreport" bib-id="may-TR149-XPathLog-01" local-id="TR149-XPathLog">

    <!-- Details Pub 4 -->

    <shorttitle>TR 149: XPath-Logic and XPathLog: A Logic-Based Approach for
    Declarative XML Data Manipulation</shorttitle>

    <techreport>Technical Report 149</techreport>

    <institute>Institut für Informatik</institute>

    <university>Universität Freiburg</university>

    <date>February</date>

    <year>2001</year>

    <month>2</month>

    <title>XPath-Logic and XPathLog: A Logic-Based Approach for Declarative XML
    Data Manipulation </title>

    <authors>

      <author>Wolfgang May</author>

    </authors>

    <abstract>

      <htmlfrag xmlns:ht="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">

        <p>

          In this work, a logic-based framework for handling XML data is proposed.
          XPath-Logic embeds an extension of the XPath query language into first-order
          logic. We give a model-theoretic semantics of XPath-Logic formulas based on
          answer-sets. XPathLog is the Horn fragment of XPath-Logic, providing a logic-
          based language for manipulating and integrating XML data. Due to the close
          relationship with XPath, the semantics of rules is easy to grasp. In contrast
          to other approaches, the XPath syntax and semantics is also used for a
          declarative specification how the database should be

          <i>updated</i>

          : when used in rule heads, XPath filters are interpreted as specifications of
          elements and properties which should be added to the database. The formal
          semantics is defined wrt. a Herbrand structure which covers the XML data
          model. XPathLog has been implemented in

          <a shape="rect" href="../../lopix">LoPiX</a>

          .

        </p>

      </htmlfrag>

    </abstract>

    <comment>

      <htmlfrag xmlns:ht="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">

        <p>

          <a shape="rect" href="TR149-XPathLog.ps">[ps-File]</a>

        </p>

        <p>

          Revised versions can be found in the

          <reference target="may-habil-01">Habilitation Thesis</reference>

          and in

          <reference target="may-TPLP-04">Theory and Practice of Logic Programming,
          2004</reference>

          .

          <br/>

          Further documentation can be found on the

          <a shape="rect" href="../../lopix/">LoPiX</a>

          project homepage.

        </p>

      </htmlfrag>

    </comment>

  </publication>

  <!-- Publication 5 -->

  <publication type="conference" bib-id="may-DBPL-01" local-id="dbpl01">

    <!-- Details of Pub 5 -->

    <shorttitle> Abstract DBPL 01</shorttitle>

    <conference>Workshop on Databases and Programming Languages (DBPL
    2001)</conference>

    <place>Frascati, Italy</place>

    <date>Sept., 8-10</date>

    <month>9</month>

    <day>8</day>

    <year>2001</year>

    <proceedings>LNCS 2397, Springer</proceedings>

    <page>165-181</page>

    <title>A Rule-based Querying and Updating Language for XML</title>

    <authors>

      <author>Wolfgang May</author>

    </authors>

    <project>XPathLog</project>

    <abstract>

      <htmlfrag xmlns:ht="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">

        <p>

          We present XPathLog as a Datalog-style extension to XPath. The querying part
          extends XPath with binding multiple variables to XML nodes which are
          "traversed" when evaluating an XPath expression. Data manipulation is done in
          a rule-based way. In contrast to other approaches, the XPath-based syntax and
          semantics is also used for a declarative specification how the database
          should be

          <i>updated</i>

          : XPath filters are interpreted as specifications of elements and properties
          which should be added to the database. In this paper, we focus on the
          theoretical aspects of XPathLog. XPathLog has been implemented in the

          <a shape="rect" href="../../lopix/">LoPiX</a>

          system.

        </p>

      </htmlfrag>

    </abstract>

    <comment>

      <htmlfrag xmlns:ht="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">

        <p>

          <a shape="rect" href="dbpl01talk.ps"> [Slides]</a>

        </p>

        <p>

          Extended versions can be found in the

          <reference target="may-habil-01">Habilitation thesis</reference>

          and in

          <reference target="may-TPLP-04">Theory and Practice of Logic Programming,
          2004</reference>

          .

          <br/>

          Further documentation can be found on the

          <a shape="rect" href="../../lopix/">LoPiX</a>

          project homepage.

        </p>

      </htmlfrag>

    </comment>

  </publication>

  <!-- Publication 6 -->

  <publication type="conference" bib-id="may-diweb-01" local-id="diweb01">

    <!-- Details of Pub 6  -->

    <shorttitle>Abstract DIWeb 01</shorttitle>

    <conference short="DIWeb 01"> CAiSE Workshop Data Integration over the Web
    (DIWeb'01)</conference>

    <place>Interlaken, Switzerland</place>

    <date>June, 4/5</date>

    <month>6</month>

    <day>4</day>

    <year>2001</year>

    <proceedings>Published as Technical Report, Univ. Montpellier (LIRM),
    France</proceedings>

    <page>2-16</page>

    <title>Integration of XML Data in XPathLog</title>

    <authors>

      <author>Wolfgang May</author>

    </authors>

    <project>XPathLog</project>

    <!--Abstract Pub 6  -->

    <abstract>

      <htmlfrag xmlns:ht="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">

        <p>

          XPathLog is a logic-based language for manipulating and integrating XML data.
          It extends the XPath query language with Prolog-style variables. Due to the
          close relationship with XPath, the semantics of rules is easy to grasp.
          XPathLog defines a semantics for XPath expressions in rule heads,

          <em>declaratively</em>

          specifying how to create and update XML trees and nodes. In this paper, we
          show how XPathLog can be used to manipulate and restructure a database
          containing several XML trees. By linking subtrees, fusing elements and
          defining synonyms, data can be restructured and integrated into result trees.
          We illustrate the practicability of the approach by excerpts of a case study
          done with the

          <a shape="rect" href="../../lopix">LoPiX</a>

          system.

        </p>

      </htmlfrag>

    </abstract>

    <comment>

      <htmlfrag xmlns:ht="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">

        <p>

          <a shape="rect" href="caise-2001.ps"> [postscript]</a>

          <br/>

          <a shape="rect" href="caise01talk.ps"> [slides]</a>

          <br/>

        </p>

        <p>

          Extended versions can be found in the

          <reference target="may-habil-01">Habilitation thesis</reference>

          and in

          <reference target="may-TPLP-04">Theory and Practice of Logic Programming,
          2004</reference>

          .

          <br/>

          Further documentation can be found on the

          <a shape="rect" href="../../lopix/">LoPiX</a>

          project homepage.

        </p>

      </htmlfrag>

    </comment>

  </publication>

  <!-- Publication 7 -->

  <publication type="conference" bib-id="may-behrends-fmldo-01" local-id="fmldo01">

    <!-- Details of Pub 7 -->

    <shorttitle> Abstract FMLDO 01</shorttitle>

    <conference short="FMLDO 2001">

      <a shape="rect" href="http://www.fmldo.org/FMII-2001/">Intl. Workshop on
    Foundations of Models and Languages for Data and Objects (FMLDO 2001)</a>

    </conference>

    <place>Roma, Italy</place>

    <date>Sept., 16-18</date>

    <month>9</month>

    <day>16</day>

    <year>2001</year>

    <proceedings>Published as Technical report, Dept. of Computer Science, Univ.
    Manchester, UK. Post-conference proceedings should have been appeared with
    Springer LNCS. </proceedings>

    <title>On an XML Data Model for Data Integration</title>

    <authors>

      <author>Wolfgang May</author>

      <author>Erik Behrends</author>

    </authors>

    <project>XPathLog</project>

    <abstract>

      <htmlfrag xmlns:ht="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">

        <p>

          We consider the problem of integrating XML data using a warehouse strategy.
          In particular, we show that the DOM model and the XML Query Data Model are
          not suitable for data integration. We present a solution by a node-labeled
          graph-based data model, called

          <i>XTreeGraph</i>

          , for an internal XML

          <i>database</i>

          that represents multiple, overlapping XML trees, or

          <i>tree views</i>

          . The practicability of the approach is shown by a rule-based XML querying
          and manipulation language, implemented in the

          <a shape="rect" href="../../lopix/">LoPiX</a>

          system.

        </p>

      </htmlfrag>

    </abstract>

    <comment>

      <htmlfrag xmlns:ht="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">

        <p>

          <a shape="rect" href="fmldo01final.ps"> [postscript]</a>

          <br/>

          <a shape="rect" href="fmldo01final.pdf"> [pdf]</a>

          <br/>

          <a shape="rect" href="fmldo01talk.ps"> [Slides]</a>

        </p>

        <p>

          An extended version can be found in the

          <reference target="may-habil-01">Habilitation thesis</reference>

          and in

          <reference target="may-TPLP-04">Theory and Practice of Logic Programming,
          2004</reference>

          .

          <br/>

          Further documentation can be found on the

          <a shape="rect" href="../../lopix/">LoPiX</a>

          project homepage.

        </p>

      </htmlfrag>

    </comment>

  </publication>

  <!-- Publication 8 -->

  <publication type="thesis" bib-id="may-habil-01">

    <!-- Details of Pub 8 -->

    <shorttitle>W.May: Habilitation Thesis</shorttitle>

    <thesis>Habilitation Thesis</thesis>

    <institute>Institut für Informatik</institute>

    <university>Universität Freiburg</university>

    <date>April</date>

    <year>2001</year>

    <month>4</month>

    <title>XPath-Logic and XPathLog: A Logic-Based Approach to XML Data
    Manipulation</title>

    <authors>

      <author>Wolfgang May</author>

    </authors>

    <linkto>http://user.informatik.uni-goettingen.de/~may/Habil/</linkto>

  </publication>

  <!-- Publication 9 -->

  <publication type="conference" bib-id="may-ideas-01" local-id="ideas01">

    <!-- Details of Pub 9 -->

    <shorttitle> Abstract IDEAS 01</shorttitle>

    <conference short="IDEAS 01"> International Database Engineering &amp; and
    Applications Workshop (IDEAS'01)</conference>

    <place>Grenoble, France</place>

    <date>July, 16-18</date>

    <month>7</month>

    <day>16</day>

    <year>2001</year>

    <proceedings>IEEE Computer Society Press</proceedings>

    <page>123-128</page>

    <title>XPathLog: A Declarative, Native XML Data Manipulation Language</title>

    <authors>

      <author>Wolfgang May</author>

    </authors>

    <project>XPathLog</project>

    <!-- Abstract of Pub 9 -->

    <abstract>

      <htmlfrag xmlns:ht="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">

        <p>

          XPathLog is a logic-based language for manipulating and integrating XML data.
          It extends the XPath query language with Prolog-style variables. Due to the
          close relationship with XPath, the semantics of rules is easy to grasp. In
          contrast to other approaches, the XPath syntax and semantics is also used for
          a declarative specification how the database should be

          <i>updated</i>

          : when used in rule heads, XPath filters are interpreted as specifications of
          elements and properties which should be added to the database. The formal
          semantics is defined wrt. a graph Herbrand structure which covers the XML
          tree data model. XPathLog has been implemented in

          <a shape="rect" href="../../">LoPiX</a>

          .

        </p>

      </htmlfrag>

    </abstract>

    <comment>

      <htmlfrag xmlns:ht="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">

        <p>

          <a shape="rect" href="ideas01talk.ps"> [Slides]</a>

        </p>

        <p>

          Extended versions can be found in the

          <reference target="may-habil-01">Habilitation thesis</reference>

          and in

          <reference target="may-TPLP-04">Theory and Practice of Logic Programming,
          2004</reference>

          .

          <br/>

          Further documentation can be found on the

          <a shape="rect" href="../../lopix/">LoPiX</a>

          project homepage.

        </p>

      </htmlfrag>

    </comment>

  </publication>

  <!-- Publication 10 -->

  <publication type="conference" bib-id="may-krdb-01" local-id="krdb01">

    <shorttitle> Abstract KRDB 01</shorttitle>

    <conference short="KRDB 2001"> International Workshop on Knowledge
    Representation meets Databases (KRDB 2001)</conference>

    <place>Roma, Italy</place>

    <date>Sept., 15</date>

    <month>9</month>

    <day>15</day>

    <year>2001</year>

    <proceedings>

    Published as Vol.45,

      <a shape="rect" href="http://sunsite.informatik.rwth-     aachen.de/Publications/CEUR-WS/index.html">CEUR Workshop Proceedings</a>

    , Technical University of Aachen (RWTH)

    </proceedings>

    <page>73-82</page>

    <title>A Framework for Generic Integration of XML Data Sources</title>

    <authors>

      <author>Wolfgang May</author>

    </authors>

    <project>XPathLog</project>

    <abstract>

      <htmlfrag xmlns:ht="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">

        <p> We consider the situation where several XML sources have to be integrated
        which are assumed to contain complementary, overlapping contents. These
        overlappings have to be detected, and then appropriate operations have to be
        applied to the internal database to generate a result view. The approach uses
        the XPathLog language for formulating queries and updates of an XML
        database. </p>

      </htmlfrag>

    </abstract>

    <comment>

      <htmlfrag xmlns:ht="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">

        <p>

          <a shape="rect" href="krdb01.ps"> [postscript]</a>

          <br/>

          <a shape="rect" href="krdb01.pdf"> [pdf]</a>

          <br/>

          <a shape="rect" href="krdb01talk.ps"> [Slides]</a>

        </p>

        <p>

          Further documentation can be found on the

          <a shape="rect" href="../../lopix/">LoPiX</a>

          project homepage.

        </p>

      </htmlfrag>

    </comment>

  </publication>

  <!-- Publication 11 -->

  <publication type="conference" bib-id="may-vldb01demo-01" local-id="vldb01demo">

    <shorttitle> Abstract VLDB01 Demo</shorttitle>

    <conference short="VLDB">

      <a shape="rect" href="http://www.dia.uniroma3.it/vldb2001">Intl. Conf. on
    Very Large Databases (VLDB)</a>

    - Demonstration Track

    </conference>

    <place>Rome, Italy</place>

    <date>Sept., 11-14</date>

    <month>9</month>

    <day>11</day>

    <year>2001</year>

    <page>707</page>

    <title>LoPiX: A System for XML Data Integration and Manipulation</title>

    <authors>

      <author>Wolfgang May</author>

    </authors>

    <project>XPathLog</project>

    <abstract>

      <htmlfrag xmlns:ht="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">

        <p>

          <a shape="rect" href="../../lopix/">LoPiX</a>

          is an implementation of XPathLog, an XML/XPath-native, rule-based programming
          language for manipulation and integration of XML documents. The main
          syntactical constructs are XPath expressions, extended with variables. Due to
          the close relationship with XPath, the semantics of rules is easy to grasp.
          In contrast to other approaches, the XPath syntax and semantics is also used
          for a declarative specification how the database should be

          <i>updated</i>

          : when used in rule heads, XPath filters are interpreted as specifications of
          elements and properties which should be added to the database. The LoPiX
          implementation provides an environment where XPathLog is complemented with
          schema information obtained from DTDs, a class concept, data-driven Web
          access and export functionality. Binaries of LoPiX together with a detailed
          paper on XPathLog can be found

          <a shape="rect" href="../../lopix/">here</a>

          .

        </p>

      </htmlfrag>

    </abstract>

    <comment>

      <htmlfrag xmlns:ht="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">

        <p>

          <a shape="rect" href="vldb01poster.ps"> [Demo Poster]</a>

        </p>

        <p>

          Due to several enquiries, here is the

          <a shape="rect" href="vldb01poster.tex">LaTeX source code</a>

          (using the a0poster package from CTAN and the

          <a shape="rect" href="../../dbicons/">dbicons.sty</a>

          ).

        </p>

        <p>

          A detailed description of the XPathLog language can be found in the

          <reference target="may-habil-01">Habilitation Thesis</reference>

          and in

          <reference target="may-TPLP-04">Theory and Practice of Logic Programming,
          2004</reference>

          .

          <br/>

          Further documentation can be found on the

          <a shape="rect" href="../../lopix/">LoPiX</a>

          project homepage.

        </p>

      </htmlfrag>

    </comment>

  </publication>

  <!-- Publication 12 -->

  <publication type="conference" bib-id="may-dagstuhl-2061-02" local-id="dagstuhl-2061-02">

    <shorttitle>Talk at Dagstuhl-Seminar 2061 </shorttitle>

    <conference>

      <a shape="rect" href="http://www.dagstuhl.de/">Dagstuhl-Seminar</a>

      <a shape="rect" href="http://www.dfki.uni-kl.de/ruleml/rmt/">"Rule Markup
      Techniques"</a>

    </conference>

    <place>Schloss Dagstuhl, Germany</place>

    <date>Feb. 3-8</date>

    <month>2</month>

    <day>3</day>

    <year>2002</year>

    <proceedings>Dagstuhl-Report No. 332</proceedings>

    <title>Data Manipulation and Integration in XML</title>

    <authors>

      <author>Wolfgang May</author>

    </authors>

    <abstract>

      <htmlfrag xmlns:ht="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">

        <p>

          <i>XPathLog</i>

          is a Logic-Programming style language for XML querying, data manipulation,
          and integration. It has been designed as a crossbreed between F-Logic (which
          has been successfully applied to semistructured data in pre-XML times) and
          XPath. Its main features are the extension of XPath with variable bindings
          and the definition of a constructive semantics for XPath atoms in rule heads.
          For updates and data integration, we favor a graph-based data model instead
          of the XML tree model: The

          <i>XTreeGraph</i>

          is an extension of the XML data model that allows multiple overlapping trees
          in a graph-like database. Result views are then defined as XML tree views
          over this internal database.

          <i>XPathLog</i>

          and the

          <i>XTreeGraph</i>

          have been implemented in the

          <a shape="rect" href="../../lopix/">

            <i>LoPiX</i>

          </a>

          system.

        </p>

        <p>

          <b>Post-Workshop Summary of the Talk:</b>

          Due to many questions at the workshop, the talk had a second title, "From F-
          Logic to XPathLog": In addition to the presentation of XPathLog, also its
          development as a reconcilation between F-Logic as a "proprietary" data model
          and language for knowledge representation and data integration, and the
          standards of the XML world is described.

        </p>

        <p>
          The XPathLog language is a Datalog-like extension of XPath for querying,
          manipulating and integrating XML data. Based on navigation and filtering, its
          basic, internal semantics is closely related to F-Logic. The querying part
          extends XPath with binding variables to XML nodes that are "traversed" when
          evaluating an XPath expression. Variables can be bound to literals, nodes,
          and even names, allowing for metadata reasoning. The variable bindings can be
          output as answers, or they can be communicated to the rule head for
          specifying updates in the database. In contrast to other approaches, the
          XPath syntax and semantics is also used for a declarative specification how
          the database should be updated: when used in rule heads, XPath filters are
          interpreted as specifications of elements and properties which should be
          added to the database.
        </p>

        <p>
          The restriction that XML uses a tree data model directly effects the
          semantics of updates: if an update specifies that some subtree of a document
          should be inserted also at another place, the subtree must be copied. Thus,
          for references into this tree, it must be decided whether they point into the
          original or into the copy; "sharing" subtrees - as in graph data models such
          as OEM or F-Logic - is not possible. On the data integration level, when
          restructuring trees, fusing nodes, and introducing synonyms, this problem
          occurs even more.
        </p>

        <p>
          Thus, as a data manipulation and integration language, XPathLog - and the
          LoPiX implementation - internally use a graph-based, edge-labeled model,
          called XTreeGraph. The XTreeGraph extends the basic XML data model by
          modeling multiple overlapping trees, and thus allows for restructuring
          existing XML trees into a densely connected graph database. XML result trees
          are then defined as XML tree views by projections from this database.
        </p>

        <p>
          Thus, the "pure" XPathLog language provides an intuitive Datalog-style
          extension of XPath for querying, data manipulation, and data integration
          which is very close to the standard syntax and semantics of XPath. Extended
          features of the language provide a class hierarchy (including nonmonotonic
          inheritance), a lightweight signature formalism (which is also used for
          defining tree views from the XTreeGraph), and data-driven Web access to
          extend the database with further XML documents. The expressiveness and
          flexibility of the full language makes it a candidate for combined handling
          of data, schema-metadata, and semantical metadata such as ontologies.
        </p>

      </htmlfrag>

    </abstract>

    <comment>

      <htmlfrag xmlns:ht="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">

        <p>

          Slides:

          <a shape="rect" href="Dagstuhl-Feb-2002.ps">[postscript]</a>

          <a shape="rect" href="Dagstuhl-Feb-2002.pdf">[pdf]</a>

        </p>

        <p>

          A detailed description of the XPathLog language can be found in the

          <reference target="may-habil-01">Habilitation thesis</reference>

          and in

          <reference target="may-TPLP-03">Theory and Practice of Logic Programming,
          2003</reference>

          .

          <br/>

          Further documentation can be found on the

          <a shape="rect" href="../../lopix/">LoPiX</a>

          project homepage.

        </p>

      </htmlfrag>

    </comment>

  </publication>

  <!-- Publication 13 -->

  <publication type="conference" bib-id="may-dexa-webs-02" local-id="dexa-webs-02">

    <shorttitle> WebS'02: Linking the Semantic Web</shorttitle>

    <conference short="WebS 02"> DEXA Workshop on Web Semantics
    (WebS'02)</conference>

    <place>Aix-en-Provence, France</place>

    <date>Sept. 3</date>

    <month>9</month>

    <day>3</day>

    <year>2002</year>

    <proceedings>Proc. DEXA 2002 Workshop, IEEE Computer Society
    Press</proceedings>

    <page>93-97</page>

    <title>Linking the Semantic Web with Existing Sources</title>

    <authors>

      <author>Wolfgang May</author>

    </authors>

    <abstract>

      <htmlfrag xmlns:ht="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">

        <p>

        The

          <i>Semantic Web</i>

        aims at providing Web data sources on a semantic level. On the other hand,
        most of the Web data itself is not suitably prepared (e.g., by annotations).
        In this paper, we describe a semantic layer that integrates existing data
        sources with the Semantic Web by combining semantic modeling with links that
        associate the semantic notions with actual data on the Web. The semantic
        level consists of specialized service providers - which can be seen as agents
        - for each application domain. Each agent contains ontological knowledge
        represented in XML where the links to the actual data are embedded as XPath
        expressions, similar to XLink. The agent uses its knowledge with an internal
        reasoning mechanism to combine the links for translating a Semantic Web query
        into a Web query that is then evaluated against the individual sources.

        </p>

      </htmlfrag>

    </abstract>

    <comment>

      <htmlfrag xmlns:ht="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">

        <p>

          <a shape="rect" href="webs02talk.ps"> [Slides (postscript)]</a>

        </p>

        <p>

          <a shape="rect" href="webs02talk.pdf"> [Slides (pdf)]</a>

        </p>

      </htmlfrag>

    </comment>

  </publication>

  <!-- Publication 14 -->

  <publication type="conference" bib-id="may-ssd-muenchen-02" local-id="ssd-   muenchen-02">

    <shorttitle>Vortrag: SSD und CL </shorttitle>

    <conference>

      <a shape="rect" href="http://www.cis.uni-       muenchen.de/people/Meuss/Herrsching02/">DFG-Rundgespräch "Theorie und
      Anwendung semistrukturierter Daten im Schnittpunkt von Informatik und
      Computerlinguistik"</a>

    </conference>

    <place>Herrsching/Ammersee, Germany</place>

    <date>Feb. 21/22</date>

    <month>2</month>

    <day>21</day>

    <year>2002</year>

    <title>Datenmanipulation und -integration in XML</title>

    <authors>

      <author>Wolfgang May</author>

    </authors>

    <abstract>

      <htmlfrag xmlns:ht="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">

        <p>
          XPathLog ist eine Datalog-artige Erweiterung von XPath als Anfrage-,
          Datenmanipulations- und -integrationssprache für XML-Daten. Dabei wird XPath
          um Variablenbindungen erweitert, bei denen die im Zuge der Auswertung eines
          XPath-Ausdrucks durchquerten XML-Knoten etc. an Variablen gebunden werden
          können. Dabei können Variablen sowohl an Literale und Knoten, als auch an
          Namen gebunden werden, um Anfragen auf Daten- sowie Schemaebene stellen zu
          können. Variablenbindungen können entweder als Antworten ausgegeben werden,
          oder an den Regelkopf weitergegeben werden um Änderungen an der Datenbasis
          auszuführen. Im Gegensatz zu anderen Ansätzen wird dabei XPath-Syntax und
          Semantik auch zur deklarativen Spezifikation von Änderungen verwendet: XPath-
          Ausdrücke im Regelkopf erhalten eine konstruktive Semantik, indem sie als
          Beschreibung der Elemente und Attribute, die der Datenbank hinzugefügt werden
          sollen, interpretiert werden.
        </p>

        <p>
          Die Einschränkung, dass XML auf einem baumartigen Datenmodell basiert hat
          dabei direkte Auswirkungen auf die Semantik von Änderungsoperationen: Wenn
          eine Änderung spezifiziert, dass ein (durch eine Anfrage) erhaltener Teilbaum
          einer XML-Instanz an einer bestimmten Stelle eingefügt werden soll, mu"s
          dieser Teilbaum kopiert werden. Damit ergibt sich die Frage, ob Referenzen,
          die in den originalen Teilbaum zeigen, angepasst werden sollen; es ist nicht
          möglich, denselben Teilbaum ein zweites Mal einzubinden (wie in
          graphbasierten Modellen wie z.B. OEM oder F-Logic). Wenn man
          Datenintegrationsprobleme, wie etwa die Restrukturierung von XML-Instanzen,
          das Verschmelzen von Knoten aus verschiedenen Bäumen, oder Synonyme
          betrachtet, wird dieses Problem noch deutlicher.
        </p>

        <p>
          Aus diesem Grund verwendet XPathLog - und die Implementierung in LoPiX -
          intern ein graphbasiertes, an den Kanten markiertes Datenmodell, das als
          XTreeGraph bezeichnet wird. Der XTreeGraph erweitert das bekannte XML-
          Datenmodell indem mehrere überlappende Bäume modelliert werden können, und
          somit die skizzierten Änderungs- und Integrationsoperationen unterstützt
          werden. Zur Integration verschiedener XML-Bäume wird aus den Eingabebäumen
          ein interner XTreeGraph erzeugt, auf dem die Ergebnisbäume durch Projektion
          als XML-Sichten definiert werden.
        </p>

        <p>
          Die "reine" XPathLog-Sprache bietet damit eine intuitive Datalog-artige
          Erweiterung von XPath zu einer Anfrage-, Datenmanipulations- und -
          integrationssprache, deren Syntax und Semantik eng an den bekannten XPath-
          Standard anknüpft. Spracherweiterungen bieten zusätzlich eine
          Klassenhierarchie (mit nichtmonotoner Wertvererbung), ein einfaches Konzept
          zur Beschreibung des Datenbankschemas (der zur Definition von XML-Views über
          dem XTreeGraph verwendet wird), sowie den Zugriff auf weitere Datenquellen im
          Web während der Auswertung eines Programms. Die Flexibilität und
          Ausdruckskraft der vollen XPathLog-Sprache erlaubt eine kombinierte
          Behandlung von Daten, Schemadaten, sowie semantischen Metadaten, wie z.B.
          Annotierungen und Ontologien.
        </p>

      </htmlfrag>

    </abstract>

    <comment>

      <htmlfrag xmlns:ht="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">

        <p>

          Folien:

          <a shape="rect" href="Munich-Feb-2002.ps">[postscript]</a>

          <a shape="rect" href="Munich-Feb-2002.pdf">[pdf]</a>

        </p>

        <p>

          A detailed description of the XPathLog language can be found in the

          <reference target="may-habil-01">Habilitation thesis</reference>

          and in

          <reference target="may-TPLP-03">Theory and Practice of Logic Programming,
          2003</reference>

          .

          <br/>

          Further documentation can be found on the

          <a shape="rect" href="../../lopix/">LoPiX</a>

          project homepage.

        </p>

      </htmlfrag>

    </comment>

  </publication>

  <!-- Publication 15 -->

  <publication type="journal" bib-id="may-ludaescher-TODS-02" local-id="tods02">

    <shorttitle> TODS: Referential Integrity</shorttitle>

    <journal>ACM Transactions on Database Systems (TODS)</journal>

    <number>27</number>

    <volume>4</volume>

    <page>343-397</page>

    <date>December</date>

    <year>2002</year>

    <month>12</month>

    <title>Understanding the Global Semantics of Referential Actions using Logic
    Rules</title>

    <authors>

      <author>Wolfgang May</author>

      <author>Bertram Ludäscher</author>

    </authors>

    <project>Referential Integrity</project>

    <abstract>

      <htmlfrag xmlns:ht="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">

        <p>

          Referential actions are specialized triggers for automatically maintaining
          referential integrity in databases. While the

          <em>local effects</em>

          of referential actions can be grasped easily, it is far from obvious what the

          <em>global semantics</em>

          of a set of interacting referential actions should be. In particular, when
          using procedural execution models, ambiguities due to the execution ordering
          can occur. No

          <em>global, declarative</em>

          semantics of referential actions has been defined yet.

        </p>

        <p>

          We show that the well-known logic programming semantics provide a natural

          <em>global</em>

          semantics of referential actions that is based on their

          <em>local</em>

          characterization: To capture the global meaning of a set

          <i>RA</i>

          of referential actions, we first define their abstract (but non-constructive)

          <em>intended semantics</em>

          . Next, we

          <em>formalize</em>

          <i>RA</i>

          as a

          <em>logic program</em>

          <i>

          P

            <sub>RA</sub>

          </i>

          . The declarative, logic programming semantics of

          <i>

          P

            <sub>RA</sub>

          </i>

          then provide the constructive,

          <em>global</em>

          semantics of the referential actions. So, we do not

          <em>define</em>

          a semantics for referential actions, but we show that there

          <em>exists</em>

          a unique

          <em>natural</em>

          semantics if one is ready to accept (i) the intuitive local semantics of
          local referential actions, (ii) the formalization of those and of the local
          "effect-propagating" rules, and (iii) the well-founded or stable model
          semantics from logic programming as "reasonable" global semantics for local
          rules.

        </p>

        <p>

          We first focus on the subset of referential actions for deletions only. We
          prove the equivalence of the logic programming semantics and the abstract
          semantics via a game-theoretic characterization, which provides additional
          insight into the meaning of interacting referential actions. In this case a

          <em>unique maximal admissible solution exists</em>

          , computable by a PTIME algorithm.

        </p>

        <p>

          Second, we investigate the general case, i.e. including modifications. We
          show that in this case there can be

          <em>multiple maximal admissible subsets</em>

          and that all maximal admissible subsets can be characterized as

          <em>3-valued stable models</em>

          of

          <i>

          P

            <sub>RA</sub>

          </i>

          . We show that for a given set of user requests, in presence of referential
          actions of the form

          <tt>ON UPDATE CASCADE</tt>

          , the admissibility check and the computation of the subsequent database
          state, and (for non-admissible updates) the derivation of debugging hints all
          are in PTIME. Thus, full referential actions can be implemented efficiently.

        </p>

      </htmlfrag>

    </abstract>

    <comment>

      <htmlfrag xmlns:ht="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">

        <p> The paper is based on previous publications and reports: </p>

        <ul>

          <li>

            <reference target="ludaescher-may-EDBT-98"> Referential Actions: From Logical
            Semantics to Implementation</reference>

            , Bertram Ludäscher, Wolfgang May, EDBT'98 (6th Intl. Conference on Extending
            Database Technology),

          </li>

          <li>

            <reference target="ludaescher-may-lausen-PODS-97"> Referential Actions as
            Logic Rules</reference>

            , Bertram Ludäscher, Wolfgang May, Georg Lausen, Proc. of 16th ACM Symposium
            on Principles of Database Systems (PODS'97).

          </li>

          <li>

            <reference target="ludaescher-may-reinert-IWS-96"> Towards a Logical
            Semantics for Referential Actions in SQL</reference>

            , Bertram Ludäscher, Wolfgang May, Joachim Reinert, Proc. 6th Intl. Workshop
            on Foundations of Models and Languages for Data and Objects: Integrity in
            Databases, Dagstuhl, Germany, 1996.

          </li>

        </ul>

      </htmlfrag>

    </comment>

  </publication>

  <!-- Publication 16 -->

  <publication type="conference" bib-id="may-www-02" local-id="www02">

    <shorttitle>WWW'02: Querying Linked XML Document Networks</shorttitle>

    <conference short="WWW 2002">11th International World Wide Web Conference
    (WWW 2002)</conference>

    <place>Honolulu, Hawaii</place>

    <date>May, 7-11</date>

    <month>5</month>

    <day>7</day>

    <year>2002</year>

    <proceedings>

      <a shape="rect" href="http://www2002.org/CDROM/alternate/166/">CDROM/online
    at http://www2002.org/CDROM/alternate/166/</a>

    </proceedings>

    <title>Querying Linked XML Document Networks in the Web</title>

    <authors>

      <author>Wolfgang May</author>

    </authors>

    <abstract>

      <htmlfrag xmlns:ht="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">

        <p>

    The W3C XML Linking Language (XLink) provides a powerful means for
    interlinking XML documents all over the world. From the database (and in
    general, querying) point of view, elements with linking semantics as
    specified by XLink can be seen as embedded views in an XML instance. Compared
    with classical databases, i.e., SQL and relational data, the situation of
    having links

          <i>inside</i>

    the data is new, raising new aspects for query languages: for using such
    documents, strategies how to handle links are required. There is not yet an
    official proposal on the interaction of interlinked XML documents using the
    XLink language and navigation/querying. We investigate a model where
    interlinked documents are regarded as

          <i>virtual</i>

    XML subtrees, i.e.,

          <i>XML views</i>

    . Several strategies are presented how to handle such subtrees, concerning
    the timepoint when the link is evaluated, and the evaluation and caching
    strategies. The evaluation strategies are influenced by capabilities of the
    linked XML servers. So far, the approach is independent from the actual
    querying language. The approach is under implementation as an extension of

          <a shape="rect" href="../../lopix/">LoPiX</a>

    , a web-aware system for XML data manipulation.

        </p>

      </htmlfrag>

    </abstract>

    <comment>

      <htmlfrag xmlns:ht="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">

        <p>

          <a shape="rect" href="www02talk.ps"> [Slides (postscript)]</a>

        </p>

        <p>

          <a shape="rect" href="www02talk.pdf"> [Slides (pdf)]</a>

        </p>

      </htmlfrag>

    </comment>

  </publication>

  <!-- Publication 16 -->

  <publication type="conference" bib-id="malheiro-may-btw-03" local-id="btw03">

    <shorttitle>BTW 2003</shorttitle>

    <conference short="BTW 03">

      <a shape="rect" href="http://www.btw2003.de/">GI-Fachtagung Datenbanksysteme
  für Business, Technologie und Web (BTW 2003)</a>

    </conference>

    <place>Leipzig, Germany</place>

    <date>February 26-28</date>

    <year>2003</year>

    <month>2</month>

    <day>26</day>

    <title>A Logical, Transparent Model for Querying Linked XML Documents</title>

    <authors>

      <author>Wolfgang May</author>

      <author>Dimitrio Malheiro</author>

    </authors>

    <abstract>

      <htmlfrag xmlns:ht="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">

        <p>

  The W3C XML Linking Language (XLink) provides a powerful means for
  interlinking XML documents all over the world. While the effects when
  browsing through linked XML documents are well-defined, there is not yet any
  proposal how to handle interlinked XML documents that make use of the XLink
  language from the database point of view, i.e., considering the data model
  and navigation/querying aspects. From the database (and in general, querying)
  point of view, elements with linking semantics can be seen as

          <em>virtual</em>

  XML subtrees, i.e.,

          <em>XML views</em>

  . Compared with classical databases, i.e., SQL and relational data, the
  situation of having links

          <em>inside</em>

  the data is new. We define a

          <em>logical, transparent</em>

  data model for linked documents. Queries are then formulated in standard
  XPath against the logical model. We propose additional attributes using the

          <tt>dbxlink</tt>

  (database-xlink) namespace for specifying the mapping from XLinks to the
  logical model.

        </p>

      </htmlfrag>

    </abstract>

    <comment>

      <htmlfrag xmlns:ht="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">

        <p>

          <a shape="rect" href="btw03talk.ps"> [Slides (postscript)]</a>

          <br/>

          <a shape="rect" href="btw03talk.pdf"> [Slides (pdf)]</a>

        </p>

      </htmlfrag>

    </comment>

  </publication>

  <!-- Publication 17 -->

  <publication type="conference" bib-id="may-colognet-03" local-id="colognet03">

    <shorttitle>BTW 2003</shorttitle>

    <conference>

      <a shape="rect" href="http://haendel.kr.tuwien.ac.at/colognet_ws/"> CoLogNET
  Workshop on Logic-based Methods for Information Integration</a>

    </conference>

    <place>Vienna, Austria</place>

    <date>August 23</date>

    <year>2003</year>

    <month>8</month>

    <day>23</day>

    <title>A Logic-Based Approach to XML Data Integration with "lazy
  materialization"</title>

    <authors>

      <author>Wolfgang May</author>

    </authors>

    <abstract>

      <htmlfrag xmlns:ht="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">

        <p> XPathLog is a Datalog-like extension of XPath for querying, manipulating
  and integrating XML data. The querying part extends XPath with binding
  variables to XML nodes that are "traversed" when evaluating an XPath
  expression. In contrast to other approaches, the XPath syntax and semantics
  is also used for a declarative specification how the database should be
  updated: when used in rule heads, XPath filters are interpreted as
  specifications of elements and properties which should be added to the
  database. Special operations for data integration include additional cross
  links (subelement relationship and attributes) between fragments of the
  original database, declaring synonym relationships between notions from
  different sources, and XML element fusion. </p>

        <p> As a data manipulation and integration language, XPathLog is originally
  based on a graph-based, edge-labeled model, called XTreeGraph. The XTreeGraph
  extends the basic XML data model by modeling multiple overlapping trees, and
  thus allows for restructuring existing XML trees into a densely connected
  graph database. XML result trees are then defined as XML tree views by
  projections from this database. The LoPiX implementation follows a "warehouse
  approach" where the integrated XTreeGraph is materialized. </p>

        <p> In the present talk, a "lazy materialization" strategy is proposed that
  does not materialize the complete internal database, and that is based on the
  original XML tree model combined with XLink: Data items that are not (yet)
  changed are integrated into the internal database as references, represented
  by XLinks. The approach uses our recent proposal for a logical, transparent
  data model for XLinked data. Only if a referenced data item is actually
  modified in course of the integration process, it is (partially) loaded into
  the database; unchanged fragments of it still being represented in a lazy way
  by XLinks. </p>

      </htmlfrag>

    </abstract>

    <comment>

      <htmlfrag xmlns:ht="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">

        <p>

          <a shape="rect" href="vienna-xlink-integra-aug-03.ps">[Slides
  (postscript)]</a>

          <br/>

          <a shape="rect" href="vienna-xlink-integra-aug-03.pdf">[Slides (pdf)]</a>

        </p>

      </htmlfrag>

    </comment>

  </publication>

  <publication type="journal" bib-id="may-dbspektrum-03" local-id="dbspektrum03">

    <shorttitle>DB-Spektrum 2003: Datenintegration</shorttitle>

    <journal>Datenbank-Spektrum</journal>

    <number>6</number>

    <volume>3</volume>

    <page>23-32</page>

    <date>June</date>

    <year>2003</year>

    <month>6</month>

    <title>Datenintegration in XML - ein regelbasierter Ansatz</title>

    <authors>

      <author>Wolfgang May</author>

    </authors>

    <abstract>

      <htmlfrag xmlns:ht="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">

        <p>

  Dieser Beitrag beschreibt die Erfahrungen, die im Rahmen des

          <a shape="rect" href="../../lopix/">LoPiX-Projektes</a>

  bei der Integration von XML-Daten gemacht wurden. Die in diesem System
  verwendete Sprache

          <em>XPathLog</em>

  ist eine Datalog-artige Erweiterung von XPath, die es erlaubt, Änderungen an
  der Datenbank in dieser erweiterten XPath-Syntax zu spezifizieren. Da solche
  Änderungen - speziell im Zuge der Datenintegration, wie z.B. die
  Restrukturierung von Datenbeständen, Verschmelzung von Knoten, und Einführung
  von Synonymen - auf dem XML-Datenmodell nicht möglich sind, basiert LoPiX auf
  dem

          <em>XTreeGraph</em>

  -Datenmodell, das nicht nur eine, sondern mehrere überlappende XML-
  Baumstrukturen verwalten kann. Als Ergebnis können dann XML-Bäume als
  Projektionen dieses Graphen (z.B. durch DTDs) erzeugt werden.

        </p>

      </htmlfrag>

    </abstract>

  </publication>

  <!-- Publication 18 -->

  <publication type="bookchapter" bib-id="lausen-may-webdb-book-03" local-id="webdb-book-03">

    <shorttitle> Anfragen, Ändern und Publizieren von XML</shorttitle>

    <book short="webdb03">

      <a shape="rect" href="http://www.dpunkt.de/buch/3-89864-189-9.html">Web &amp;
  Datenbanken</a>

  (

      <a shape="rect" href="http://dbs.uni-   leipzig.de/webdb/kapitel.html">Kapitelübersicht</a>

  )

    </book>

    <editor>Erhard Rahm und Gottfried Vossen, editors</editor>

    <publisher>dpunkt-Verlag</publisher>

    <isbn>ISBN 3-89864-189-9</isbn>

    <page>65-100</page>

    <date>January</date>

    <year>2003</year>

    <month>1</month>

    <title>Anfragen, Ändern und Publizieren von XML</title>

    <authors>

      <author>Georg Lausen</author>

      <author>Wolfgang May</author>

    </authors>

    <project>XML</project>

    <abstract>

      <htmlfrag xmlns:ht="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">

        <p> Dieses Kapitel hat Anfragesprachen, Datenmanipulation und -transformation
  von XML-Daten zum Inhalt. Dabei wird sowohl die Entwicklung der Konzepte
  beschrieben, als auch eine Einführung in die gegenwärtig populärsten
  Sprachen, XPath und XQuery, gegeben. XML-Anfragesprachen gehen zurück auf die
  frühen XSL Patterns und XQL, aus denen sich XPath als
  Adressierungsformalismus entwickelte, der die Grundlage für mächtigere
  Sprachen zu XML bildet. In diesem Kapitel werden die Anfragesprachen XML-QL,
  sowie das auf XPath basierende Quilt, aus dem dann XQuery hervorging,
  beschrieben. Mittlerweile wurden zu diesen bis dahin reinen Anfragesprachen
  auch Konzepte zur Datenmanipulation vorgeschlagen, die als Spracherweiterung
  zu XQuery auch bereits implementiert sind. Weiterhin wird in diesem Kapitel
  die Transformation von XML-Daten beschrieben, die letztlich eine Grundlage
  für die Präsentation in HTML ist. </p>

      </htmlfrag>

    </abstract>

  </publication>

  <!-- Publication 19  -->

  <publication type="journal" bib-id="lausen-may-IS-04" local-id="IS04">

    <shorttitle>IS 2004: Information Integration</shorttitle>

    <journal>Information Systems </journal>

    <number>29</number>

    <volume>1</volume>

    <page>59-91</page>

    <date>January</date>

    <year>2004</year>

    <month>1</month>

    <title>A Uniform Framework for Integration of Information from the
  Web</title>

    <authors>

      <author>Wolfgang May</author>

      <author>Georg Lausen</author>

    </authors>

    <abstract>

      <htmlfrag xmlns:ht="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">

        <p>

  We discuss a system that implements an integrated framework for Web
  exploration, wrapping, data integration, and querying. Here, the
  "integration" applies in three aspects: the data model and the functionality,
  and the architecture. The core of the approach is a unified framework - i.e.,
  data model and language - in which all tasks are performed. We regard the Web
  and its contents as a unit, represented in a semi-structured, object-oriented
  data model: the Web structure, given by its hyperlinks, the parse-trees of
  Web pages, and its contents are all included in the internal world model of
  the system. Additionally, the application-level model is immediately
  generated as an overlay of this source-level model. The model is complemented
  by a rule-based object-oriented language which is extended by Web accessing
  capabilities and structured document analysis. This language is implemented
  by a central reasoning engine. The advantage of our unified approach is that
  the same data manipulation and query language can be used for all tasks,
  i.e., accessing Web pages, wrapping, data integration, and querying
  information. Thus, these tasks are not necessarily separated, but can be
  closely intertwined. Additionally, by reusing the source-level model for
  generating the application-level model, there is no overhead for
  communication and mapping between different data formats. In particular, we
  present a methodology for reusing generic rule patterns for typical
  extraction, integration, and restructuring tasks. In an abstract sense, the
  system contains a universal wrapper, which can be applied to arbitrary Web
  pages that the system considers during information processing. Equipped with
  suitably intelligent rules, the system can potentially explore initially
  unknown parts of the Web, thus coping with the steady growth of the Web. We
  show the practicability of our approach by using the

          <a shape="rect" href="http://www.informatik.uni-   freiburg.de/~dbis/florid">FLORID</a>

  system.

        </p>

      </htmlfrag>

    </abstract>

  </publication>

  <!-- Publication 20 -->

  <publication type="journal" bib-id="may-TPLP-04" local-id="TPLP04">

    <shorttitle>TPLP 2004: XPathLog</shorttitle>

    <journal>Theory and Practice of Logic Programming</journal>

    <number>4</number>

    <volume>3</volume>

    <page>499-526</page>

    <date>December</date>

    <year>2004</year>

    <month>12</month>

    <title>XPath-Logic and XPathLog: A Logic-Programming Style XML Data
  Manipulation Language</title>

    <authors>

      <author>Wolfgang May</author>

    </authors>

    <abstract>

      <htmlfrag xmlns:ht="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">

        <p> We define XPathLog as a Datalog-style extension of XPath. XPathLog
  provides a clear, declarative language for querying and manipulating XML
  whose perspectives are especially in XML data integration. </p>

        <p>

  In our characterization, the formal semantics is defined wrt. an

          <em>edge-labeled graph-based</em>

  model which covers the XML data model. We give a complete, logic-based
  characterization of XML data and the main language concept for XML, XPath.
  XPath-Logic extends the XPath language with variable bindings and embeds it
  into first-order logic. XPathLog is then the Horn fragment of XPath-Logic,
  providing a Datalog-style, rule-based language for querying and manipulating
  XML data. The model-theoretic semantics of XPath-Logic serves as the base of
  XPathLog as a logic-programming language, whereas also an equivalent answer-
  set semantics for evaluating XPathLog queries is given. In contrast to other
  approaches, the XPath syntax and semantics is also used for a declarative
  specification how the database should be

          <em>updated</em>

  : when used in rule heads, XPath filters are interpreted as specifications of
  elements and properties which should be added to the database.

        </p>

        <p>

  The paper is available online at

          <a shape="rect" href="http://arxiv.org/abs/cs.DB/0311038">arXiv.org</a>

  .

        </p>

        <p>

  The paper is an excerpt of the Habilitation Thesis

          <reference target="may-habil-01">A Logic-Based Approach to XML Data
  Integration</reference>

  (2001).

          <br/>

  XPathLog has been implemented in the

          <a shape="rect" href="../../lopix">LoPiX</a>

  project.

        </p>

      </htmlfrag>

    </abstract>

    <comment>

      <htmlfrag xmlns:ht="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">

        <p> Preliminary results have been presented in </p>

        <ul>

          <li>

            <reference target="may-vldb01demo-01">Intl. Conf. on Very Large Databases
  (VLDB) 2001</reference>

  - Demonstration Track,

          </li>

          <li>

            <reference target="may-DBPL-01">Workshop on Databases and Programming
  Languages (DBPL 2001)</reference>

  ,

          </li>

          <li>

            <reference target="may-behrends-fmldo-01">Workshop on Foundations of Models
  and Languages for Data and Objects (FMLDO 2001)</reference>

  ,

          </li>

        </ul>

      </htmlfrag>

    </comment>

  </publication>

  <!-- Publication 21 -->

  <publication type="thesis" bib-id="may-dipl-95">

    <shorttitle>W.May: Diploma Thesis</shorttitle>

    <thesis>Diploma Thesis</thesis>

    <institute>Fakultät für Informatik</institute>

    <university>Universität Karlsruhe</university>

    <date>February</date>

    <year>1995</year>

    <month>2</month>

    <title> Protokollverifikation in Temporallogik: Evolving Algebras und ein
  Tableaukalkül</title>

    <authors>

      <author>Wolfgang May</author>

    </authors>

    <project>Dynamics</project>

    <project>Formal Methods</project>

    <project>Temporal Logics</project>

    <linkto>http://user.informatik.uni-goettingen.de/~may/Diplom/</linkto>

  </publication>

  <publication type="conference" bib-id="may-schmitt-fapr-96" local-id="fapr96">

    <shorttitle>Abstract FAPR'96</shorttitle>

    <conference short="fapr 96">International Conference on Formal and Applied
  Practical Reasoning (FAPR'96)</conference>

    <place>Bonn, Germany</place>

    <date>June 3-7</date>

    <year>1996</year>

    <month>6</month>

    <day>3</day>

    <proceedings>LNCS 1085, Springer</proceedings>

    <page>399-413</page>

    <title>A Tableau Calculus For First-Order Branching Time Logic</title>

    <authors>

      <author>Wolfgang May</author>

      <author>Peter H. Schmitt</author>

    </authors>

    <project>Temporal Logic</project>

    <project>Dynamics</project>

    <abstract>

      <htmlfrag xmlns:ht="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">

        <p>

  Tableau-based proof systems have been designed for many logics extending
  classical first-order logic. This paper proposes a sound tableau calculus for
  temporal logics of the first-order CTL-family. Until now, a tableau calculus
  has only been presented for the propositional version of CTL. The calculus
  considered operates with prefixed formulas and may be regarded as an instance
  of a labelled deductive system. The prefixes allow an explicit partial
  description of states and paths of a potential Kripke counter model in the
  tableau. It is possible in particular to represent path segments of finite
  but arbitrary length which are needed to process reachability formulas.
  Furthermore, we show that by using prefixed formulas and explicit
  representation of paths it becomes possible to express and process fairness
  properties without having to resort to full CTL

          <sup>*</sup>

  . The approach is suitable for use in interactive proof-systems.

        </p>

      </htmlfrag>

    </abstract>

    <comment>

      <htmlfrag xmlns:ht="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">

        <p>

          <a shape="rect" href="fapr96.ps.gz"> [PS-File]</a>

          <br/>

          <a shape="rect" href="fapr96sl.ps.gz"> [Slides]</a>

        </p>

      </htmlfrag>

    </comment>

  </publication>

  <!-- Publication 21 -->

  <publication type="conference" bib-id="ludaescher-may-reinert-IWS-96" local-id="iws96">

    <shorttitle>IWS: Referential Integrity</shorttitle>

    <conference short="LID96"> 6th Intl. Workshop on Foundations of Models and
  Languages for Data and Objects (FMLDO'96)</conference>

    <place>Dagstuhl, Germany</place>

    <date>September 16-20</date>

    <year>1996</year>

    <month>9</month>

    <day>16</day>

    <proceedings>Proceedings: University of Magdeburg, Faculty of Computer
  Science, Preprint No. 4, 1996</proceedings>

    <page>57-72</page>

    <title>Towards a Logical Semantics for Referential Actions in SQL</title>

    <authors>

      <author>Bertram Ludäscher</author>

      <author>Wolfgang May</author>

      <author>Joachim Reinert</author>

    </authors>

    <project>Referential Integrity</project>

    <abstract>

      <htmlfrag xmlns:ht="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">

        <p>

  We investigate a logical semantics which unambiguously specifies the meaning
  of SQL-like referential actions of the form ON DELETE CASCADE and ON DELETE
  RESTRICT. The semantics is given by a translation of referential actions into
  logical rules. The proposed semantics is less restrictive than the standard
  SQL semantics, yet preserves all referential integrity constraints. First, a
  preliminary set of rules is introduced which rejects a set of user requests
  if a single request is rejected. Subsequently, a refined translation is
  presented using

          <i>Statelog</i>

  , a state-oriented Datalog extension which allows to define active and
  deductive rules within a unified framework. We show that our semantics yields
  the maximal admissible subset of a given set of user requests. Apart from the
  Statelog formalization, a three-valued formalization based on the well-
  founded semantics and an equivalent game-theoretic specification are
  presented, which give further insight into the problem of ambiguity of
  triggers.

        </p>

      </htmlfrag>

    </abstract>

    <comment>

      <htmlfrag xmlns:ht="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">

        <p>

          <a shape="rect" href="iws96.ps.gz"> [PS-File]</a>

          <br/>

          <a shape="rect" href="iws96-slides.ps.gz"> [Slides of the talk]</a>

        </p>

        <p>

  Followup papers have been published in

          <reference target="ludaescher-may-lausen-PODS-97">PODS 1997</reference>

  and

          <reference target="may-ludaescher-TODS-02">TODS 27(4), 2002</reference>

  .

          <br/>

  An extended version containing these results can be found in

          <reference target="may-ludaescher-TODS-02">Understanding the Global Semantics
  of Referential Actions using Logic Rules</reference>

  , Wolfgang May, Bertram Ludäscher, ACM Transactions on Database Systems
  (TODS), 27(4), 2002.

        </p>

      </htmlfrag>

    </comment>

  </publication>

  <!-- Publication 22 -->

  <publication type="conference" bib-id="ludaescher-may-lausen-lid-96" local-id="lid96">

    <shorttitle>LID: Nested Transactions</shorttitle>

    <conference short="LID96"> Intl. Workshop on Logic in Databases
  (LID'96)</conference>

    <place>San Miniato, Italy</place>

    <date>July 1-3</date>

    <year>1996</year>

    <month>7</month>

    <day>1</day>

    <proceedings>LNCS 1154, Springer</proceedings>

    <page>197-222</page>

    <title>Nested Transactions in a Logical Language for Active Rules</title>

    <authors>

      <author>Bertram Ludäscher</author>

      <author>Wolfgang May</author>

      <author>Georg Lausen</author>

    </authors>

    <project>Statelog</project>

    <project>Logic Programming</project>

    <project>Active Databases</project>

    <project>Dynamics</project>

    <abstract>

      <htmlfrag xmlns:ht="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">

        <p>

  We present a hierarchically structured transaction-oriented concept for a
  rule-based active database system. In previous work, we have proposed

          <i>Statelog</i>

  as a unified framework for active and deductive rules. Following the need for
  better structuring capabilities, we introduce

          <i>procedures</i>

  as a means to group semantically related rules and to encapsulate their
  behavior. In addition to executing elementary updates, procedures can be
  called, thereby defining (sub)transactions which may perform complex
  computations. A Statelog procedure is a set of ECA-style Datalog rules
  together with an import/export interface. System-immanent frame and procedure
  rules ensure both propagation of facts and processing of results of committed
  subtransactions. Thus, Statelog programs specify a nested transaction model
  which allows a much more structured and natural modeling of complex
  transactions than previous approaches. Two equivalent semantics for a
  Statelog program

          <i>P</i>

  are given: (i) a logic programming style semantics by a compilation into a
  logic program, and (ii) a model-theoretic Kripke-style semantics. While (ii)
  serves as a

          <i>conceptual</i>

  model of active rule behavior and allows to reason about properties of the
  specified transactions, (i) -- together with the appropriate execution model
  -- yields an operational semantics and can be used as an implementation of

          <i>P</i>

  .

        </p>

      </htmlfrag>

    </abstract>

    <comment>

      <htmlfrag xmlns:ht="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">

        <p>

          <a shape="rect" href="lid96.ps.gz"> [PS-File]</a>

          <br/>

          <a shape="rect" href="lid96-slides.ps.gz"> [Slides of the talk]</a>

        </p>

      </htmlfrag>

    </comment>

  </publication>

  <!-- Publication 23 -->

  <publication type="conference" bib-id="may-ludaescher-lausen-dood-wfs-   97" local-id="dood97-wfs">

    <shorttitle>Abstract DOOD'97</shorttitle>

    <conference short="dood-wfs 97">5th Intl. Conf. on Deductive and Object-
  Oriented Databases (DOOD'97)</conference>

    <place>Montreux, Switzerland</place>

    <date>December 8-12</date>

    <year>1997</year>

    <month>12</month>

    <day>8</day>

    <proceedings>LNCS 1341, Springer</proceedings>

    <page>320-336</page>

    <title>Well-Founded Semantics for Deductive Object-Oriented Database
  Languages </title>

    <authors>

      <author>Wolfgang May</author>

      <author>Bertram Ludäscher</author>

      <author>Georg Lausen</author>

    </authors>

    <project>Well-Founded</project>

    <abstract>

      <htmlfrag xmlns:ht="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">

        <p>

  We present a well-founded semantics for deductive object-oriented database
  languages by applying the alternating-fixpoint characterization of the well-
  founded model to them. In order to compute the state sequence, states are
  explicitely integrated by making them first-class citizens of the underlying
  language. The concept is applied to

          <i>Florid</i>

  , an implementation of

          <i> F-Logic</i>

  , previously supporting only inflationary negation. Using our approach, well-
  founded models of F-Logic programs can be computed. The method is also
  applicable to arbitrary languages which provide a sufficiently flexible
  syntax and semantics. Given an implementation of the underlying database
  language, any program given in this language can be evaluated wrt. the well-
  founded semantics.

        </p>

      </htmlfrag>

    </abstract>

    <comment>

      <htmlfrag xmlns:ht="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">

        <p>

          <a shape="rect" href="dood97-wfs.ps.gz"> [PS-File]</a>

          <br/>

          <a shape="rect" href="dood97sl.ps.gz"> [Extended set of slides]</a>

        </p>

      </htmlfrag>

    </comment>

  </publication>

  <!-- Publication 24 -->

  <publication type="conference" bib-id="may-fapr-97" local-id="fapr97">

    <shorttitle>Abstract FAPR'97</shorttitle>

    <conference short="fapr 97">International Joint Conference on Qualitative and
  Quantitative Practical Reasoning (ECSQARU/FAPR '97)</conference>

    <place>Bad Honnef, Germany</place>

    <date>June 9-12</date>

    <year>1997</year>

    <month>6</month>

    <day>9</day>

    <proceedings>LNCS 1244, Springer</proceedings>

    <page>436-450</page>

    <title>Process Modeling with Different Qualities of Knowledge</title>

    <authors>

      <author>Wolfgang May</author>

    </authors>

    <project>Knowledge Modeling</project>

    <project>Dynamics</project>

    <project>Formal Methods</project>

    <project>Temporal Logics</project>

    <abstract>

      <htmlfrag xmlns:ht="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">

        <p> For modeling structured processes with different levels of atomic
  actions, classical linear or branching time Kripke structures with first-
  order states are insufficient: They do not provide any means for modeling
  independent parallel threads of activity which have to be joined at some
  point, action refinement, or procedure concepts. In all three cases, it is
  important to distinguish facts resp. knowledge derived in the current thread
  of activity from facts which are not concerned in this activity. This problem
  is also closely related to the frame problem. </p>

        <p> In this paper, hierarchical Kripke structures are introduced for modeling
  hierarchically structured processes, also coping with the different qualities
  of knowledge arising in this context: every state consists of a total first-
  order interpretation, which gives the state as-is, and a partial first-order
  interpretation containing all procedure knowledge which has been derived in
  the current thread of activity. </p>

        <p> A correct and complete set of axioms is presented for reasoning about
  hierarchical Kripke structures. </p>

      </htmlfrag>

    </abstract>

    <comment>

      <htmlfrag xmlns:ht="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">

        <p>

          <a shape="rect" href="fapr97.ps.gz"> [PS-File]</a>

          <br/>

          <a shape="rect" href="fapr97sl.ps.gz"> [Slides]</a>

        </p>

      </htmlfrag>

    </comment>

  </publication>

  <!-- Publication 25 -->

  <publication type="conference" bib-id="ludaescher-may-lausen-PODS-97" local-id="pods97">

    <shorttitle> PODS: Referential Integrity</shorttitle>

    <conference short="PODS 97">16th. ACM Symposium on Principles of Database
  Systems (PODS 97)</conference>

    <place>Tucson, Arizona, USA</place>

    <date>May 12-14</date>

    <year>1997</year>

    <month>5</month>

    <day>12</day>

    <proceedings>ACM Press</proceedings>

    <page>217-224</page>

    <title>Referential Actions as Logical Rules</title>

    <authors>

      <author>Bertram Ludäscher</author>

      <author>Wolfgang May</author>

      <author>Georg Lausen</author>

    </authors>

    <project>Referential Integrity</project>

    <abstract>

      <htmlfrag xmlns:ht="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">

        <p>

  Referential actions are specialized triggers used to automatically maintain
  referential integrity. While their local behavior can be grasped easily, it
  is far from clear what the combined effect of a set of referential actions,
  i.e., their global semantics should be. For example, different execution
  orders may lead to ambiguities in determining the final set of updates to be
  applied. To resolve these problems, we propose an abstract logical framework
  for rule-based maintenance of referential integrity: First, we identify
  desirable abstract properties like

          <i>admissibility</i>

  of updates which lead to a non-constructive global semantics of referential
  actions. We obtain a constructive definition by formalizing a set of
  referential actions

          <i>RA</i>

  as logical rules, and show that the declarative semantics of the resulting
  logic program

          <i>

  P

            <sub>RA</sub>

          </i>

  captures the intended abstract semantics: The well-founded model of

          <i>

  P

            <sub>RA</sub>

          </i>

  yields a unique set of updates, which is a safe, sceptical approximation of
  the set of all maximal admissible updates; the third truth-value

          <i>undefined</i>

  is assigned to all controversial updates. Finally, we show how to obtain a
  characterization of all maximal admissible subsets of a given set of updates
  using certain maximal stable models.

        </p>

      </htmlfrag>

    </abstract>

    <comment>

      <htmlfrag xmlns:ht="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">

        <p>

          <a shape="rect" href="pods97.ps.gz"> [PS-File]</a>

          <br/>

          <a shape="rect" href="pods97-foiles.ps.gz"> [Slides of the talk]</a>

        </p>

        <p> An extended version can be found in </p>

        <ul>

          <li>

            <reference target="may-ludaescher-TODS-02">Understanding the Global Semantics
  of Referential Actions using Logic Rules</reference>

  , Wolfgang May, Bertram Ludäscher, ACM Transactions on Database Systems
  (TODS), 27(4), 2002.

          </li>

        </ul>

      </htmlfrag>

    </comment>

  </publication>

  <!-- Publication 26 -->

  <publication type="conference" bib-id="may-schlepphorst-lausen-rids-   97" local-id="rids97">

    <shorttitle>Abstract RIDS'97</shorttitle>

    <conference short="rids 97">3rd International Workshop on Rules in Database
  Systems (RIDS'97)</conference>

    <place>Skövde, Sweden</place>

    <date>June 26-28</date>

    <year>1997</year>

    <month>6</month>

    <day>26</day>

    <proceedings>LNCS 1312, Springer</proceedings>

    <page>20-34</page>

    <title>Integrating Dynamic Aspects into Deductive Object-Oriented
  Databases </title>

    <authors>

      <author>Wolfgang May</author>

      <author>Christian Schlepphorst</author>

      <author>Georg Lausen</author>

    </authors>

    <project>Dynamics</project>

    <abstract>

      <htmlfrag xmlns:ht="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">

        <p>

  We show how the dynamics of database systems can be modeled by making states
  first-class citizens in an object-oriented deductive database language. With
  states at the same time acting as objects, methods, or classes, several
  concepts of dynamic entities can be implemented, allowing an intuitive,
  declarative modeling of the application domain. Exploiting the natural
  stratification induced by the state sequence, the approach also provides an
  implementable operational semantics. The method is applicable to arbitrary
  object-oriented deductive database languages which provide a sufficiently
  flexible syntax and semantics. Provided an implementation of the underlying
  database language, any system specification in the presented framework is
  directly executable, thus unifying specification, implementation, and
  metalanguage for proving properties of a system. The concept is applied to F-
  Logic. Besides the declarative semantics given by the rules of a State-F-
  Logic program, the use of F-Logic's inheritance semantics for modeling states
  provides an effective operational semantics exploiting the naturally given
  state-stratification. State-F-Logic programs can be executed using the

          <a shape="rect" href="http://www.informatik.uni-   freiburg.de/~dbis/florid">Florid</a>

  implementation.

        </p>

      </htmlfrag>

    </abstract>

    <comment>

      <htmlfrag xmlns:ht="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">

        <p>

          <a shape="rect" href="rids97.ps.gz"> [PS-File]</a>

          <br/>

          <a shape="rect" href="rids97sl.ps.gz"> [Slides]</a>

        </p>

      </htmlfrag>

    </comment>

  </publication>

  <!-- Publication 27 -->

  <publication type="conference" bib-id="may-tab-97" local-id="tab97">

    <shorttitle>Abstract TABLEAUX'97</shorttitle>

    <conference short="tab 97">International Conference on Analytic Tableaux and
  Related Methods (TABLEAUX'97)</conference>

    <place>Pont-à-Mousson, France</place>

    <date>May 13-16</date>

    <year>1997</year>

    <month>5</month>

    <day>13</day>

    <proceedings>LNCS 1227, Springer</proceedings>

    <page>261-275</page>

    <title>Proving Correctness of Labeled Transition Systems by Semantic
  Tableaux </title>

    <authors>

      <author>Wolfgang May</author>

    </authors>

    <project>Temporal Logics</project>

    <project>Dynamics</project>

    <project>Formal Methods</project>

    <abstract>

      <htmlfrag xmlns:ht="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">

        <p> The paper presents a method for formally proving correctness of processes
  specified by transition systems which is based on a tableau calculus for an
  extended temporal logic. The model-theoretic semantics is given by labeled
  Kripke structures, incorporating information about the actions performed in
  transitions. Extending first-order CTL for handling action labels, the multi-
  modal logic MCTL is defined which is well-suited for specifying transition
  systems and their properties. For MCTL, a tableau semantics and -calulus is
  presented, allowing formal verification. </p>

      </htmlfrag>

    </abstract>

    <comment>

      <htmlfrag xmlns:ht="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">

        <p>

          <a shape="rect" href="tab97.ps.gz"> [PS-File]</a>

          <br/>

          <a shape="rect" href="tab97sl.ps.gz"> [Slides]</a>

        </p>

      </htmlfrag>

    </comment>

  </publication>

  <publication type="conference" bib-id="may-tapsoft-97" local-id="tapsoft97">

    <shorttitle>Abstract TAPSOFT'97</shorttitle>

    <conference short="tapsoft 97">7th International Joint Conference on the
  Theory and Practice of Software Development (TAPSOFT'97)</conference>

    <place>Lille, France</place>

    <date>April 14-18</date>

    <year>1997</year>

    <month>4</month>

    <day>14</day>

    <proceedings>LNCS 1214, Springer</proceedings>

    <page>535-549</page>

    <title>Specifying Complex and Structured Systems with Evolving
  Algebras </title>

    <authors>

      <author>Wolfgang May</author>

    </authors>

    <project>Formal Methods</project>

    <abstract>

      <htmlfrag xmlns:ht="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">

        <p>

  This paper presents an approach for specifying complex, structured systems
  with Evolving Algebras by means of aggregation and composition. Evolving
  algebras provide a formal method for

          <i>executable</i>

  specifications which has been employed for specifying several algorithms and
  programming languages. With its transition system-like rule-based syntax, the
  concept is as well very intuitive as well-suited for formal reasoning and
  verification.

        </p>

        <p> Following the need for structuring capabilities in specification
  frameworks, the paper proposes a concept for hierarchically structuring
  Evolving Algebras corresponding to the semantics of the system to be modeled,
  allowing to build up complex systems from simpler ones by several
  combinators. The concept can be generalized to arbitrary rule-based state-
  oriented formalisms. </p>

        <p> In such systems, transitions regarded as atomic on the corresponding
  level are allowed to be specified by computations performed by sub-Evolving-
  Algebras instead of single rules. The subsystems provide a natural way of
  encapsulating data and behaviour while a computation is running.
  Communication is done via distinguished locations accessible to the
  participating systems. </p>

      </htmlfrag>

    </abstract>

    <comment>

      <htmlfrag xmlns:ht="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">

        <p>

          <a shape="rect" href="tapsof97.ps.gz">[PS-File]</a>

          <br/>

          <a shape="rect" href="taps97sl.ps.gz">[Slides]</a>

        </p>

        <p>

  The paper is based on

          <br/>

        </p>

        <ul>

          <li>

            <a shape="rect" href="ea180596.ps">[Slides]</a>

  given at "Workshop on Evolving Algebras", May 17-19, 1996, Schloß
  Eringerfeld, Germany

          </li>

          <li>

            <a shape="rect" href="report-96-ea.ps">[Report]</a>

          </li>

        </ul>

      </htmlfrag>

    </comment>

  </publication>

  <!-- Publication 28 -->

  <publication type="journal" bib-id="ludaescher-himmeroeder-lausen-may-   schlepphorst-is-98" local-id="IS98">

    <shorttitle> IS 23(8) FLORID</shorttitle>

    <journal short="IS 98">Information Systems, Special Issue on Semistructured
  Data,</journal>

    <number>23</number>

    <volume>8</volume>

    <page>589-612</page>

    <date>December</date>

    <year>1998</year>

    <month>12</month>

    <title>Managing Semistructured Data with FLORID: A Deductive Object-Oriented
  Perspective</title>

    <authors>

      <author>Bertram Ludäscher</author>

      <author>Rainer Himmeröder</author>

      <author>Georg Lausen</author>

      <author>Wolfgang May</author>

      <author>Christian Schlepphorst</author>

    </authors>

    <project>Information Extraction</project>

    <abstract>

      <htmlfrag xmlns:ht="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">

        <p>

  The closely related research areas

          <i>management of semistructured data</i>

  and languages for

          <i>querying the Web</i>

  have recently attracted a lot of interest. We argue that languages supporting
  deduction and object-orientation (

          <i>dood</i>

  languages) are particularly suited in this context:

          <i>Object-orientation</i>

  provides a flexible common data model for combining information from
  heterogeneous sources and for handling partial information. Techniques for
  navigating in object-oriented databases can be applied to semistructured
  databases as well, since the latter may be viewed as (very simple) instances
  of the former.

          <i>Deductive rules</i>

  provide a powerful framework for expressing complex queries in a high-level,
  declarative programming style.

          <br/>

  We elaborate on the management of semistructured data and show how
  reachability queries involving general path expressions and the extraction of
  data paths in the presence of cyclic data can be handled. We then propose a
  formal model for querying structure and contents of Web data and present its
  declarative semantics. A main advantage of our approach is that it brings
  together the above-mentioned issues in a unified, formal framework and -
  using the

          <a shape="rect" href="http://www.informatik.uni-   freiburg.de/~dbis/florid/"> FLORID</a>

  system - supports rapid prototyping and experimenting with all these
  features. Concrete examples illustrate the concise and elegant programming
  style supported by FLORID and substantiate the above-mentioned claims.

        </p>

      </htmlfrag>

    </abstract>

  </publication>

  <!-- Publication 29 -->

  <publication type="conference" bib-id="himmeroeder-kandazia-ludaescher-may-   lausen-DDLP-98" local-id="ddlp98">

    <shorttitle>Search, Analysis, and Integration of Web Documents: A Case Study
  with FLORID</shorttitle>

    <conference short="DDLP 98">Intl. Workshop on Deductive Databases and Logic
  Programming (DDLP'98)</conference>

    <place>Manchester, UK</place>

    <date>June 20</date>

    <year>1998</year>

    <month>6</month>

    <day>20</day>

    <proceedings>GMD Report 22/1998</proceedings>

    <page>47-58</page>

    <title>Search, Analysis, and Integration of Web Documents: A Case Study with
  FLORID</title>

    <authors>

      <author>Rainer Himmeröder</author>

      <author>Paul-Th. Kandzia</author>

      <author>Bertram Ludäscher</author>

      <author>Wolfgang May</author>

      <author>Georg Lausen</author>

    </authors>

    <project>Information Extraction</project>

    <abstract>

      <htmlfrag xmlns:ht="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">

        <p> Languages supporting deduction and object-orientation seem particularly
  promising for querying and reasoning about structure and contents of the Web,
  and for the integration of information from heterogeneous sources. FLORID, an
  implementation of the deductive object-oriented language F-logic, has been
  extended to provide a declarative semantics for querying the Web. This
  extension allows extraction and restructuring of data from the Web and a
  seamless integration with local data. Since the functionality of wrappers and
  mediators is integrated into a single declarative language, the development
  of advanced applications based on the Web as an information source is
  significantly simplified. This claim is substantiated using a comprehensive
  example. </p>

      </htmlfrag>

    </abstract>

    <comment>

      <htmlfrag xmlns:ht="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">

        <p>

          <a shape="rect" href="ddlp98.ps.gz"> [PS-File]</a>

          <br/>

          <a shape="rect" href="ddlp-slides.ps"> [Slides]</a>

        </p>

      </htmlfrag>

    </comment>

  </publication>

  <!-- Publication 30 -->

  <publication type="thesis" bib-id="may-diss-98">

    <shorttitle>W.May: PhD Thesis</shorttitle>

    <thesis>Dissertation/PhD Thesis</thesis>

    <institute>Institut für Informatik</institute>

    <university>Universität Freiburg</university>

    <date>Mai</date>

    <year>1998</year>

    <month>5</month>

    <title>Integrated Static and Dynamic Modeling of Processes</title>

    <authors>

      <author>Wolfgang May</author>

    </authors>

    <project>Dynamics</project>

    <project>Formal Methods</project>

    <project>Temporal Logics</project>

    <linkto>http://user.informatik.uni-goettingen.de/~may/Diss/</linkto>

  </publication>

  <!-- Publication 31 -->

  <publication type="conference" bib-id="ludaescher-may-EDBT-98" local-id="edbt98">

    <shorttitle> EDBT: Referential Integrity</shorttitle>

    <conference short="EDBT 98">6th. Intl. Conference on Extending Database
  Technology (EDBT'98)</conference>

    <place>Valencia, Spain</place>

    <date>March 23-27</date>

    <year>1998</year>

    <month>3</month>

    <day>23</day>

    <proceedings>LNCS 1377, Springer</proceedings>

    <page>404-418</page>

    <title>Referential Actions: From Logical Semantics to Implementation</title>

    <authors>

      <author>Bertram Ludäscher</author>

      <author>Wolfgang May</author>

    </authors>

    <project>Referential Integrity</project>

    <abstract>

      <htmlfrag xmlns:ht="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">

        <p>

  Referential actions (rac's) are specialized triggers used to automatically
  maintain referential integrity. While their local effects can be grasped
  easily, it is far from obvious what the global semantics of a set RA of
  interacting rac's should be. To capture the intended meaning of RA, we first
  present an abstract non-constructive semantics. By formalizing RA as a logic
  program P

          <sub>RA</sub>

  , a constructive semantics is obtained. The equivalence of the logic
  programming semantics and the abstract semantics is proven using a game-
  theoretic characterization, which provides additional insight into the
  meaning of rac's. As shown in previous work, for general rac's it may be
  infeasible to compute all

          <em>maximal admissible</em>

  solutions. Therefore, we focus on a tractable subset, i.e., rac's without
  modifications. We show that in this case a unique maximal admissible solution
  exists, and derive a PTIME algorithm for computing this solution. In case a
  set U of user requests is not admissible, a maximal admissible subset of U is
  suggested.

        </p>

      </htmlfrag>

    </abstract>

    <comment>

      <htmlfrag xmlns:ht="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">

        <p>

          <a shape="rect" href="edbt98.ps.gz">[edbt98.ps.gz]</a>

        </p>

        <p> This paper elaborates on the practical aspects of </p>

        <ul>

          <li>

            <reference target="ludaescher-may-lausen-PODS-97"> Referential Actions as
  Logic Rules</reference>

  , Bertram Ludäscher, Wolfgang May, Georg Lausen, Proc. of 16th ACM Symposium
  on Principles of Database Systems (PODS'97).

          </li>

        </ul>

        <p> An extended version can be found in </p>

        <ul>

          <li>

            <reference target="may-ludaescher-TODS-02">Understanding the Global Semantics
  of Referential Actions using Logic Rules</reference>

  , Wolfgang May, Bertram Ludäscher, ACM Transactions on Database Systems
  (TODS), 27(4), 2002.

          </li>

        </ul>

      </htmlfrag>

    </comment>

  </publication>

  <!-- Publication 32 -->

  <publication type="conference" bib-id="ludaescher-himmeroeder-may-ki-ws-   98" local-id="ki-ws98">

    <shorttitle>KI 98: Querying Web Data with FLORID</shorttitle>

    <conference short="ki-ws 98">Workshop Deklarative KI-Methoden zur
  Implementierung und Nutzung von Systemen in Netzen, KI-98</conference>

    <place>Bremen, Germany</place>

    <date>September 16</date>

    <year>1998</year>

    <month>9</month>

    <day>16</day>

    <proceedings>GMD Report 29/1998</proceedings>

    <page>65-79</page>

    <title>Techniques and Rule Patterns for Declaratively Querying Web Data with
  FLORID</title>

    <authors>

      <author>Bertram Ludäscher</author>

      <author>Rainer Himmeröder</author>

      <author>Wolfgang May</author>

    </authors>

    <project>Information Extraction</project>

    <abstract>

      <htmlfrag xmlns:ht="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">

        <p>

          <a shape="rect" href="http://www.informatik.uni-   freiburg.de/~dbis/florid/">FLORID </a>

  is an implementation of the deductive object-oriented database language F-
  logic and has recently been extended to provide a declarative semantics for
  querying the Web. By means of several illustrative examples, we show how
  \florid's rule-based logical language can be used to extract, query, and
  analyze data from the Web.

        </p>

      </htmlfrag>

    </abstract>

    <comment>

      <htmlfrag xmlns:ht="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">

        <p>

          <a shape="rect" href="ki98-ws.ps.gz"> [PS-File]</a>

          <br/>

          <a shape="rect" href="ki98-ws-slides.ps.gz"> [Slides]</a>

        </p>

      </htmlfrag>

    </comment>

  </publication>

  <!-- Publication 33 -->

  <publication type="bookchapter" bib-id="lausen-ludaescher-may-moc-98" local-id="moc98">

    <shorttitle>On Logical Foundations of Active Databases</shorttitle>

    <book short="moc 98">Transactions and Change in Logic Databases</book>

    <editor>Hendrik Decker, Burkhard Freitag, Michael Kifer, and Andrei Voronkov,
  editors</editor>

    <publisher>Springer LNCS 1472</publisher>

    <page>69-106</page>

    <year>1998</year>

    <title>On Active Deductive Databases: The Statelog Approach</title>

    <authors>

      <author>Georg Lausen</author>

      <author>Bertram Ludäscher</author>

      <author>Wolfgang May</author>

    </authors>

    <project>On Active Deductive Databases: The Statelog Approach</project>

    <project>Active Databases</project>

    <abstract>

      <htmlfrag xmlns:ht="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">

        <p>

  After briefly reviewing the basic notions and terminology of active rules and
  relating them to production rules and deductive rules, respectively, we
  survey a number of formal approaches to active rules. Subsequently, we
  present our own state-oriented logical approach to active rules which
  combines the declarative semantics of deductive rules with the possibility to
  define updates in the style of production rules and active rules. The
  resulting language

          <b>

            <i>Statelog</i>

          </b>

  is surprisingly simple, yet captures many features of active rules including
  composite event detection and different coupling modes. Thus, it can be used
  for the formal analysis of rule properties like termination and expressive
  power. Finally, we show how nested transactions can be modeled in Statelog,
  both from the operational and the model-theoretic perspective.

        </p>

      </htmlfrag>

    </abstract>

    <comment>

      <htmlfrag xmlns:ht="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">

        <p>

          <a shape="rect" href="moc98.ps.gz">ps-file</a>

        </p>

      </htmlfrag>

    </comment>

  </publication>

  <!-- Publication 34 -->

  <publication type="bookchapter" bib-id="lausen-ludaescher-may-rolis-   98" local-id="rolis98">

    <shorttitle> On Logical Foundations of Active Databases</shorttitle>

    <book short="rolis 98">Logics for Databases and Information Systems</book>

    <editor>Jan Chomicki and Gunter Saake, editors</editor>

    <publisher>Kluwer Academic Publishers</publisher>

    <isbn>ISBN 0-7923-8129-7</isbn>

    <page>389-422</page>

    <year>1998</year>

    <title>On Logical Foundations of Active Databases</title>

    <authors>

      <author>Georg Lausen</author>

      <author>Bertram Ludäscher</author>

      <author>Wolfgang May</author>

    </authors>

    <project>Active Databases</project>

    <abstract>

      <htmlfrag xmlns:ht="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">

        <p>

  In this chapter, we present work on logical foundations of active databases.
  After introducing the basic notions and terminology, we give a short overview
  of research on foundations of active rules. Subsequently, we present a
  specific state-oriented logical approach to active rules which aims at
  combining the declarative semantics of deductive rules with the possibility
  to define updates in the style of production rules. The resulting language

          <i>Statelog</i>

  models (flat) transactions as a sequence of intermediate transitions, where
  each transition is defined using deductive rules. Since Statelog programs
  correspond to a specific class of locally stratified logic programs, they
  have a unique intended model. Finally, after studying further fundamental
  properties like expressive power and termination behavior, a Statelog
  framework for active rules is presented. Although the framework is
  surprisingly simple, it allows to model many essential features of active
  rules, including immediate and deferred rule execution, and composite events.
  Different alternatives for enforcing termination are proposed leading to
  tractable subclasses of the language. Finally, we show that certain classes
  of Statelog programs correspond to Datalog programs with production rule
  semantics (i.e., with inflationary or noninflationary fixpoint semantics).

        </p>

      </htmlfrag>

    </abstract>

    <comment>

      <htmlfrag xmlns:ht="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">

        <p>

          <a shape="rect" href="http://wwwiti.cs.uni-   magdeburg.de/~saake/ldbis.html"> [Book]</a>

        </p>

      </htmlfrag>

    </comment>

  </publication>

  <!-- Publication 35 -->

  <publication type="conference" bib-id="may-kandzia-WLP-98" local-id="wlp98">

    <shorttitle>Abstract WLP'98</shorttitle>

    <conference short="WLP'98">13. Workshop logische Programmierung
  (WLP'98)</conference>

    <place>Vienna, Austria</place>

    <date>October, 6-8</date>

    <year>1998</year>

    <month>10</month>

    <day>06</day>

    <proceedings>Technical Report 1843-1998-10, Institut für Informationssysteme,
  TU Wien</proceedings>

    <title>Nonmonotonic Inheritance in Object-Oriented Deductive Database
  Languages</title>

    <authors>

      <author>Wolfgang May</author>

      <author>Paul-Thomas Kandzia</author>

    </authors>

    <project>Inheritance</project>

    <abstract>

      <htmlfrag xmlns:ht="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">

        <p> Deductive object-oriented frameworks integrate logic rules and
  inheritance. There, specific problems arise: Due to the combination of
  deduction and inheritance, (a) deduction can take place depending on
  inherited facts, thus raising indirect conflicts, and (b) also the class
  hierarchy and -membership is subject to deduction. </p>

        <p> From this point of view, we investigate the application of the extension
  semantics of Default Logic to deductive object-oriented database
  languages. </p>

        <p> By restricting the problem to Horn programs and a special type of
  defaults tailored to the semantics of inheritance, a forward-chaining
  construction of a Herbrand-style representation of extensions is
  possible. </p>

        <p> This construction is compared with a solution as implemented in the F-
  Logic system Florid which is based on a combination of classical deductive
  fixpoints and an inheritance-trigger mechanism. </p>

        <p> From the F-Logic point of view, the main contribution of the report is to
  provide a connection between inheritance-canonic models as defined in [Kifer-
  Lausen-Wu-JACM-95] and classical AI frameworks. </p>

      </htmlfrag>

    </abstract>

    <comment>

      <htmlfrag xmlns:ht="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">

        <p>

          <a shape="rect" href="WLP98.ps"> [ps-File]</a>

          <br/>

          <a shape="rect" href="WLP98sl.ps"> [Slides]</a>

        </p>

        <p>

  The full paper,

          <reference target="may-kandzia-TR-Inheritance-99"> Technical Report
  114 </reference>

  , Institut für Informatik, Universität Freiburg, Jan. 1999.

        </p>

        <p> </p>

        <p>

  A

          <reference target="kandzia-may-JLC-Inheritance-01">revised
  version</reference>

  is published in

          <b>

            <i>Journal of Logic and Computation</i>

          </b>

  , 11(4), 2001.

        </p>

      </htmlfrag>

    </comment>

  </publication>

  <!-- Publication 36 -->

  <publication type="techreport" bib-id="may-kandzia-TR-Inheritance-99" local-id="TR-Inheritance">

    <shorttitle>TR 131: Inheritance</shorttitle>

    <techreport short="TR-Inheritance 99">Technical Report 114</techreport>

    <place>Freiburg, Germany</place>

    <university>Universität Freiburg</university>

    <institute>Institut für Informatik</institute>

    <number>114</number>

    <date>January</date>

    <year>1999</year>

    <month>1</month>

    <title>Nonmonotonic Inheritance in Object-Oriented Deductive Database
  Languages</title>

    <authors>

      <author>Wolfgang May</author>

      <author>Paul-Thomas Kandzia</author>

    </authors>

    <project>Inheritance</project>

    <abstract>

      <htmlfrag xmlns:ht="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">

        <p> Deductive object-oriented frameworks integrate logic rules and
  inheritance. There, specific problems arise: Due to the combination of
  deduction and inheritance, (a) deduction can take place depending on
  inherited facts, thus raising indirect conflicts, and (b) also the class
  hierarchy and -membership is subject to deduction. </p>

        <p> From this point of view, we investigate the application of the extension
  semantics of Default Logic to deductive object-oriented database
  languages. </p>

        <p> By restricting the problem to Horn programs and a special type of
  defaults tailored to the semantics of inheritance, a forward-chaining
  construction of a Herbrand-style representation of extensions is
  possible. </p>

        <p> This construction is compared with a solution as implemented in the F-
  Logic system FLORID which is based on a combination of classical deductive
  fixpoints and an inheritance-trigger mechanism. </p>

        <p> From the F-Logic point of view, the main contribution of the report is to
  investigate the relationship between inheritance-canonic models as defined in
  [Kifer-Lausen-Wu-JACM-95] and classical AI frameworks: we show that the
  semantics which is defined and implemented for F-Logic coincides with the
  standard semantics of Default Logic and Inheritance Networks. In this report,
  we restrict ourselves to scalar methods. </p>

      </htmlfrag>

    </abstract>

    <comment>

      <htmlfrag xmlns:ht="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">

        <p>

          <a shape="rect" href="TR114-Inheritance.ps">[ps-File]</a>

        </p>

        <p>

  A

          <reference target="may-kandzia-WLP-98">preliminary version</reference>

  has been presented at

          <b>

            <i> 13. Workshop logische Programmierung - WLP'98 </i>

          </b>

  , Vienna, Oct. 6-8, 1998.

        </p>

        <p>

  A

          <reference target="kandzia-may-JLC-Inheritance-00">revised
  version</reference>

  is published in

          <b>

            <i> Journal of Logic and Computation</i>

          </b>

  , 11(4), 2001.

        </p>

      </htmlfrag>

    </comment>

  </publication>

  <!-- Publication 37 -->

  <publication type="techreport" bib-id="may-TR-Mondial-99" local-id="TR-   Mondial">

    <shorttitle>TR 131: The Mondial Case Study</shorttitle>

    <techreport short="TR-Mondial 99">Technical Report 131</techreport>

    <place>Freiburg, Germany</place>

    <university> Universität Freiburg</university>

    <institute>Institut für Informatik</institute>

    <number>131</number>

    <date>December</date>

    <year>1999</year>

    <month>12</month>

    <title>Information Extraction and Integration with FLORID: The MONDIAL Case
  Study</title>

    <authors>

      <author>Wolfgang May</author>

    </authors>

    <abstract>

      <htmlfrag xmlns:ht="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">

        <p>

  For accessing and processing this information provided on the Web, there is a
  need for integration of data from different, heterogeneous sources. Languages
  for this purpose have to serve for querying the web, extracting information
  from semistructured data, and restructuring the results. In [LHL+98] we argue
  that languages supporting deduction and object-orientation are particularly
  suited in this context; we proposed a formal model for querying structure and
  contents of Web data. A main advantage of our approach is that it brings
  together the above-mentioned issues in a unified, formal framework. The
  approach is implemented in the

          <a shape="rect" href="http://www.informatik.uni-   freiburg.de/~dbis/florid/"> FLORID</a>

  system [HLL98] which is an implementation of the deductive object-oriented
  database language F-Logic [KLW95].

        </p>

        <p> This report substantiates the above claims by a case-study using FLORID:
  We show how several information sources on the Web containing political and
  geographical data are integrated to a geographical database using FLORID. The
  case study illustrates the trade-off gained from an integrated Web-querying
  and data manipulation language, supporting a concise and elegant programming
  style. Using a deductive language, a process of rapid prototyping and
  refinement of the program -- implementing both a wrapper and a mediator --
  can be easily followed: the program consists of a skeleton of generic
  wrapping rules [MHL+99], augmented by refining rules and application-specific
  rules. </p>

      </htmlfrag>

    </abstract>

    <comment>

      <htmlfrag xmlns:ht="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">

        <p>

          <a shape="rect" href="TR131-Mondial.ps">[ps-File]</a>

        </p>

        <ul>

          <li>

  The report

            <reference target="may-lausen-tr136-infoextr">Information Extraction from the
  Web</reference>

  describes the underlying Framework.

          </li>

          <li>

  The homepage of the

            <a shape="rect" href="../../Mondial/">Mondial</a>

  database contains the F-Logic programs and the database in F-Logic, Oracle,
  and XML formats.

          </li>

        </ul>

      </htmlfrag>

    </comment>

  </publication>

  <!-- Publication 38 -->

  <publication type="conference" bib-id="may-dagstuhl-99" local-id="dagstuhl99talk">

    <shorttitle>Dagstuhl-Seminar: Web</shorttitle>

    <conference short="dagstuhl99talk 99">

      <a shape="rect" href="http://www.dagstuhl.de/"> Dagstuhl-Seminar</a>

  "Declarative Data Access on the Web"

    </conference>

    <place>Schloss Dagstuhl, Germany</place>

    <date>September 12-17</date>

    <year>1999</year>

    <month>9</month>

    <day>12</day>

    <proceedings>Dagstuhl-Report No. 251</proceedings>

    <title>Information Extraction from the Web with FLORID</title>

    <authors>

      <author>Wolfgang May</author>

    </authors>

    <project>Information Extraction from the Web with FLORID</project>

    <abstract>

      <htmlfrag xmlns:ht="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">

        <p> The talk presents an integrated architecture where Web exploration,
  wrapping, mediation, and querying is done in a monolithic system. The system
  is based on a unified framework -- i.e., data model and language -- in which
  all tasks are done. We regard the Web and its contents as a unit, represented
  in an object-oriented data model: the Web structure, given by its hyperlinks,
  the parse-trees of Web pages, and its contents all becomes part of the
  internal world model of the system. The advantage of this unified view is
  that the same data manipulation and querying language can be used for the Web
  structure and the application-semantic model: The model is complemented by a
  rule-based object-oriented language which is extended by Web access
  capabilities and structured document analysis and allows for accessing the
  Web, wrapping, mediating, and querying information. Due to this integration,
  a system in this architecture can be equipped with Web navigation and
  exploration functionality. We present generic rule patterns for typical
  extraction, integration, and restructuring tasks using this framework. We
  show the practicability of our approach by using the FLORID system. The
  approach is illustrated by two case-studies. </p>

      </htmlfrag>

    </abstract>

    <comment>

      <htmlfrag xmlns:ht="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">

        <p>

          <a shape="rect" href="dagst99.ps">[Slides]</a>

        </p>

      </htmlfrag>

    </comment>

  </publication>

  <!-- Publication 39 -->

  <publication type="conference" bib-id="may-idm-99" local-id="idm99">

    <shorttitle>Abstract IDM99</shorttitle>

    <conference short="idm 99">International Workshop on Internet Data Management
  (IDM'99)</conference>

    <place>Firenze, Italy</place>

    <date>September 2</date>

    <year>1999</year>

    <month>9</month>

    <day>2</day>

    <proceedings>Proc. DEXA 99 Workshop, IEEE Computer Society
  Press</proceedings>

    <page>721-725</page>

    <title>Modeling and Querying Structure and Contents of the Web</title>

    <authors>

      <author>Wolfgang May</author>

    </authors>

    <project>Information Extraction</project>

    <abstract>

      <htmlfrag xmlns:ht="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">

        <p> For accessing and processing the information provided on the Web, there
  is a need for extraction, restructuring, and integration of semistructured
  data from autonomous, heterogeneous sources. In this paper, we regard the Web
  and its contents as a unit, represented in an object-oriented data model: the
  Web structure (inter-document level), given by its hyperlinks, the parse-
  trees of Web pages (intra-document level), and their contents. The model is
  complemented by a rule-based object-oriented language which is extended by
  Web access capabilities and allows for and navigation in the unified model.
  We show the practicability of our approach by using the FLORID system. </p>

      </htmlfrag>

    </abstract>

    <comment>

      <htmlfrag xmlns:ht="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">

        <p>

          <a shape="rect" href="http://computer.org/conferen/proceed/dexa/0281/02810721   abs.htm"> [The Paper (IEEE Digital Library)]</a>

          <br/>

          <a shape="rect" href="idm99sl.ps"> [Slides]</a>

        </p>

      </htmlfrag>

    </comment>

  </publication>

  <!-- Publication 40 -->

  <publication type="talk" bib-id="may-suny-99" local-id="sunytalk99">

    <shorttitle>Information Extraction from the Web with FLORID </shorttitle>

    <talk>Guest talk</talk>

    <place>Stony Brook, NY</place>

    <date>June 14</date>

    <year>1999</year>

    <month>6</month>

    <day>14</day>

    <title>Information Extraction from the Web with FLORID</title>

    <authors>

      <author>Wolfgang May</author>

    </authors>

    <project>Information Extraction</project>

    <abstract>

      <htmlfrag xmlns:ht="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">

        <p> FLORID is an implementation of F-Logic by the database group at the
  University of Freiburg (Germany). In the talk, the Web extension of FLORID is
  presented. It allows for wrapping, restructuring and integrating data from
  the Web, in a unified framework by using F-Logic rules as unique language for
  programming and querying. The object-oriented Web Model is based on the
  classes url and webdoc for representing the skeleton of a relevant Web
  fragment. The intra-document structure is represented by parse-trees which
  are integrated into the Web skeleton. In the information retrieval task,
  objects in the extended Web skeleton are identified and restructured into an
  object-oriented model of the application domain. The wrapping task is done by
  analyzing the F-Logic representation of the parse-tree and matching with perl
  regular expressions. The approach is illustrated by a case study which
  integrates geographical data from different sources. </p>

        <p> Structure of the talk: </p>

        <ul>

          <li> The Web Model: What we can do with FLORID for Web Data Extraction </li>

          <li> Implementation: How is this implemented in FLORID</li>

          <li> Practice: How is it used?</li>

          <li> Demonstration: The Mondial Case Study</li>

          <li> Lessons we have learnt and further ideas.</li>

        </ul>

      </htmlfrag>

    </abstract>

    <comment>

      <htmlfrag xmlns:ht="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">

        <p>

          <a shape="rect" href="suny.ps"> [Slides]</a>

        </p>

      </htmlfrag>

    </comment>

  </publication>

  <!--Publication 41  -->

  <publication type="conference" bib-id="" local-id="tab99">

    <shorttitle>Abstract TABLEAUX'97</shorttitle>

    <conference short="tab 99">International Conference on Analytic Tableaux and
  Related Methods (TABLEAUX'99)</conference>

    <place>Albany, NY</place>

    <date>June 7-11</date>

    <year>1999</year>

    <month>6</month>

    <day>7</day>

    <proceedings>LNCS 1617, Springer</proceedings>

    <page>232-246</page>

    <title>A Tableau Calculus for a Temporal Logic with Temporal
  Connectives </title>

    <authors>

      <author>Wolfgang May</author>

    </authors>

    <project>Dynamics</project>

    <project>Formal Methods</project>

    <project>Temporal Logics</project>

    <abstract>

      <htmlfrag xmlns:ht="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">

        <p> The paper presents a tableau calculus for a linear time temporal logic
  for reasoning about processes and events in concurrent systems. The logic is
  based on temporal connectives in the style of Transaction Logic and explicit
  quantification over states. The language extends first-order logic with
  sequential and parallel conjunction, parallel disjunction, and temporal
  implication. Explicit quantification over states via state variables allows
  to express temporal properties which cannot be formulated in modal logics.
  Using the tableau representation of temporal Kripke structures presented for
  CTL which represents states by prefix terms, explicit quantification over
  states is integrated into the tableau calculus by an adaptation of the delta-
  rule from first-order tableau calculi to the linear ordering of the universe
  of states. Complementing the CTL calculus, the paper shows that this tableau
  representation is both suitable for modal temporal logics and for logics
  using temporal connectives. </p>

      </htmlfrag>

    </abstract>

    <comment>

      <htmlfrag xmlns:ht="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">

        <p>

          <a shape="rect" href="tab99ECL.ps"> [postscript]</a>

          <br/>

          <a shape="rect" href="tab99sl.ps"> [Slides]</a>

        </p>

      </htmlfrag>

    </comment>

  </publication>

  <!-- Publication 42 -->

  <publication type="talk" bib-id="may-tuw-99" local-id="tuwtalk99">

    <shorttitle>Information Extraction from the Web</shorttitle>

    <talk>Guest talk</talk>

    <place>Database and Artificial Intelligence Group at TU Vienna,
  Austria</place>

    <date>November 5</date>

    <year>1999</year>

    <month>11</month>

    <day>5</day>

    <title>Information Extraction from the Web with FLORID</title>

    <authors>

      <author>Wolfgang May</author>

    </authors>

    <project>Information Extraction</project>

    <abstract>

      <htmlfrag xmlns:ht="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">

        <p> FLORID is an implementation of F-Logic by the database group at the
  University of Freiburg (Germany). In the talk, the Web extension of FLORID is
  presented. It allows for wrapping, restructuring and integrating data from
  the Web, in a unified framework by using F-Logic rules as unique language for
  programming and querying. The object-oriented Web Model is based on the
  classes url and webdoc for representing the skeleton of a relevant Web
  fragment. The intra-document structure is represented by parse-trees which
  are integrated into the Web skeleton. In the information retrieval task,
  objects in the extended Web skeleton are identified and restructured into an
  object-oriented model of the application domain. The wrapping task is done by
  analyzing the F-Logic representation of the parse-tree and by matching with
  perl regular expressions. The approach is illustrated by two case
  studies. </p>

      </htmlfrag>

    </abstract>

    <comment>

      <htmlfrag xmlns:ht="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">

        <p>

          <a shape="rect" href="tuw99.ps"> [Slides]</a>

        </p>

      </htmlfrag>

    </comment>

  </publication>

  <!-- Publication 43 -->

  <publication type="conference" bib-id="may-ludaescher-lausen-himmeroeder-   wwwcm-99" local-id="wwwcm99">

    <shorttitle>Abstract WWWCM99</shorttitle>

    <conference short="wwwcm 99">International Workshop on the World-Wide Web and
  Conceptual Modeling (WWWCM'99)</conference>

    <place>Paris, France</place>

    <date>November 15-18</date>

    <year>1999</year>

    <month>11</month>

    <day>15</day>

    <proceedings>LNCS 1727, Springer</proceedings>

    <page>307-320</page>

    <title>A Unified Framework for Wrapping, Mediating and Restructuring
  Information from the Web</title>

    <authors>

      <author>Wolfgang May</author>

      <author>Bertram Ludäscher</author>

      <author>Georg Lausen</author>

      <author>Rainer Himmeröder</author>

    </authors>

    <project>World-Wide Web and Conceptual Modeling</project>

    <abstract>

      <htmlfrag xmlns:ht="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">

        <p> The goal of information extraction from the Web is to provide an
  integrated view on heterogeneous information sources via a common data model
  and query language. A main problem with current approaches is that they rely
  on very different formalisms and tools for wrappers and mediators, thus
  leading to an "impedance mismatch" between the wrapper and mediator level. In
  contrast, our approach integrates wrapping and mediation in a unified
  framework based on an object-oriented data model which represents both the
  Web structure and the data of the application domain. Wrappers and mediators
  are written in a rule-based object-oriented language which is augmented with
  features for Web access and structured document analysis, i.e., pattern
  matching by regular expressions and SGML parsing. In this paper, we develop
  generic, reusable rule patterns for typical extraction, integration, and
  restructuring tasks using this framework. We show the practicability of our
  approach by using the FLORID system. </p>

      </htmlfrag>

    </abstract>

    <comment>

      <htmlfrag xmlns:ht="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">

        <p>

          <a shape="rect" href="wwwcm99.ps"> [postscript]</a>

          <br/>

          <a shape="rect" href="wwwcm99sl.ps"> [Slides]</a>

        </p>

      </htmlfrag>

    </comment>

  </publication>

</publications>
